<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A prospect of Hungary, and Transylvania with a catalogue of the kings of the one, and the princes of the other; together with an account of the qualities of the inhabitants, the commodites of the countries, the chiefest cities, towns, and strong-holds, rivers, and mountains. Whereunto is added an historical narrative of the bloody wars amongst themselves, and with the Turks; continued to this present year 1664. As also a brief description of Bohemia, Austria, Bavaria, Steirmark, Croatia, Dalmatia, Moravia, Silesia, Carinthia, Carniola, and some other adjacent countries contained in a mapp affixed hereunto: in which mapp all the places that are in the power of the Turk have a crescent, or half moon over them; and those in the possession of the Christians have a cross.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833672</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833672</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38150</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38150)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2176:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A prospect of Hungary, and Transylvania with a catalogue of the kings of the one, and the princes of the other; together with an account of the qualities of the inhabitants, the commodites of the countries, the chiefest cities, towns, and strong-holds, rivers, and mountains. Whereunto is added an historical narrative of the bloody wars amongst themselves, and with the Turks; continued to this present year 1664. As also a brief description of Bohemia, Austria, Bavaria, Steirmark, Croatia, Dalmatia, Moravia, Silesia, Carinthia, Carniola, and some other adjacent countries contained in a mapp affixed hereunto: in which mapp all the places that are in the power of the Turk have a crescent, or half moon over them; and those in the possession of the Christians have a cross.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Miller at the Gilded Acorn in St Pauls Church-yard, near the little North Door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1661-1664 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  History --  1526-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Transylvania (Romania) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38150:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38150:1"/>
            <p>A PROSPECT OF HUNGARY, AND TRANSYLVANIA, With a Catalogue of the Kings of the one, and the Princes of the other;</p>
            <p>Together with an account of the qualities of the Inhabitants, the Commodites of the Countries, the chiefeſt Cities, Towns, and Strong-holds, Rivers, and Mountains.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added An Hiſtorical Narration of the bloody Wars amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and with the <hi>Turks;</hi> continued to this preſent Year 1664.</p>
            <p>As alſo A brief Deſcription of <hi>Bohemia, Auſtria, Bavaria, Steirmark, Croatia, Dalmatia, Moravia, Sileſia, Carinthia, Carniola,</hi> and ſome other adjacent Countries contained in a Mapp affixed hereunto:</p>
            <p>In which Mapp all the places that are in the power of the <hi>Turk,</hi> have a Creſcent, or half Moon over them; and thoſe in the poſſeſſion of the Chriſtians have a Croſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Miller</hi> at the Gilded Acorn in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, near the little North Door. 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38150:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38150:2"/>
            <head>The Deſcription of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> with the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the late Wars, and Changes there.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngary</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania,</hi> and <hi>Walachia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hungary</hi> deſcribed.</note> On the Weſt with <hi>Stiria,</hi> or <hi>Steirmark, Austria,</hi> and <hi>Moravia:</hi> On the North with the <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains, which are a long and craggy ledge of Hills, beginning near the City of <hi>Presburg,</hi> and the borders of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and ſo paſs on in a continuall courſe till they come to the very <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea, dividing <hi>Hungary</hi> from <hi>Poland,</hi> and parting <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and <hi>Moldovia,</hi> from <hi>Ruſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigra,</hi> and <hi>Podolia,</hi> two Provinces of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Kingdom: and on the South with <hi>Sclavonia,</hi> and ſome part of <hi>Dacia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hungary</hi> extendeth in length from <hi>Presburg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The length, &amp; breadth of it.</note> along the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now,</hi> to the borders of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> for the ſpace of three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles, &amp; one hundred and ninty of the ſame miles in breadth: The longeſt Summers Day in the Southern parts, is fifteen hours, and a half, and not above ſixteen hours in the Northermoſt parts.<note place="margin">The Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it.</note> 
               <hi>Hungary</hi> is commonly divided into the <hi>Upper Hungary,</hi> and the <hi>Lower:</hi> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper</hi> lies on the North of the River <hi>Danow,</hi> out of the bounds, and territories of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire: The <hi>Lower</hi> lies on the South of the <hi>Danow,</hi> and comprehends all <hi>Pannonia Inferior,</hi> and part of <hi>Superior,</hi> which were formerly two <hi>Roman</hi> Provinces.</p>
            <p>The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Hungary</hi> is ſubdivided (before the coming in of the <hi>Turks</hi>) into thirty two Counties, thar is to ſay, twenty four on the Weſt ſide of <hi>Tibiſcus</hi> (or the River <hi>Tiſſe</hi>) and eight on the Eaſt ſide of the ſame River. The <hi>Lower</hi> is divided into eighteen Counties, of which ten were between the <hi>Danow,</hi> and the River <hi>Dravus;</hi> and the other ſix between
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38150:3"/> the <hi>Danow,</hi> and the River <hi>Savus.</hi> But this Diviſion, and the Subdiviſions depending upon it, being, ſince the coming in of the <hi>Turks</hi> almoſt out of uſe, we will now look upon it as it ſtands divided for the preſent (or lately did) betwixt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, as King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> by a mixt Title of Deſcent, and Election, and the Great <hi>Turk,</hi> as Lord of the moſt part of it by Arms and Conqueſt, two parts of three at leaſt being in his Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The chief Towns in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors Part.</note>The chief places in the Emperors Part are, 1. <hi>Sabria,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently the chief City of <hi>Pannonia Superior,</hi> by the <hi>Hungarians</hi> called <hi>Kimarorubath,</hi> and by the Dutch, <hi>Leibnits.</hi> 2. <hi>Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the Birth-place of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Jerome,</hi> one of the four chief Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the <hi>Latine</hi> Church, ſituate in the confines of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> commonly called <hi>Strigman.</hi> 3. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gria,</hi> a Biſhops See. 4. <hi>Nitri,</hi> a Biſhops See alſo, on the River <hi>Boch.</hi> 5. <hi>Sopran,</hi> on the Borders of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> 6. <hi>Komara,</hi> a ſtrong piece, ſtanding in an Iſland of the ſame name, made by the <hi>Danow.</hi> 7. <hi>Presburg</hi> on the edge of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> on the North ſide of that River, called by the <hi>Latines, Poſſonium:</hi> It's ſeated in a pleaſant healthful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try on the River <hi>Lyet,</hi> which there falls into the <hi>Danow:</hi> in the Suburbs whereof, upon the top of an high Mountain, ſtandeth a Stately Caſtle, the ordinary reſidence of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, as Kings of <hi>Hungary.</hi> For though it be a little City, and not very beautiful, yet being ſecured by the neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> it hath been made the Regal City of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> ſince <hi>Buda</hi> was loſt. Before the walls hereof died Count <hi>Dampier,</hi> one of the chief Commanders of the Emperor <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> the ſecond, in the wars of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia.</hi> 8. <hi>Gran,</hi> called <hi>Strigonium,</hi> which was taken by the <hi>Turks, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1534, and won again by the Chriſtians 1595, at which time S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardour</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Tho. Arundels</hi> valour.</note> carried himſelf ſo gallantly by forcing the Water-Tower, and taking thence with his own hands, the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Banner,<note place="margin">His re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note> that the Emperor <hi>Rodulph</hi> created him a Count of the Empire, and King <hi>James</hi> afterwards made him Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardour.</hi> It is ſeated on the <hi>Danow,</hi> but oppoſite to the mouth of the River <hi>Gran,</hi> which ariſing in the upper
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38150:3"/> 
               <hi>Hungary,</hi> doth there end its courſe. Its alſo the ſeat of an Archbiſhop, who is the Primate of <hi>Hungary.</hi> 9. <hi>Raab,</hi> which ſtands on the meeting of the <hi>Danow</hi> with the River <hi>Rab,</hi> coming out of the Lower <hi>Hungary:</hi> its called in <hi>Latine Jaurinum.</hi> It was heretofore memorable for being the bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the two <hi>Pannonia</hi>'s, <hi>Superior, &amp; Inferior,</hi> hereabouts divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Of late its famous for a ſtrong Fortreſs againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> by whom it was taken <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1594. but not long after again recovered by the Induſtry of Monſieur <hi>de Vandre Court,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Gentleman. 10. <hi>Newſol,</hi> or <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel,</hi> a ſtrong Town in the higher <hi>Hungary,</hi> not far from the Spring-head of the River <hi>Gran,</hi> which in the year 1621. proved fatal to that great Commander the Court of <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> who at the ſiege hereof (the Town being kept by the <hi>Hungarians</hi> againſt the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond) loſt his Life. For going privatly to view ſome places of advantage whereby to make a general aſſault, he fell into an Ambuſh of <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who ſuddenly ſet upon him, diſcomfitted his ſmall Party, kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, firſt his Horſe under him, and at laſt himſelf, having in that Skirmiſh received ſixteen wounds. Here was alſo ſlain with him at the ſame time, <hi>Torquato,</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> Prince, Count <hi>Verdugo,</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Earl, and one of the <hi>Gouragas,</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Mantua.</hi> It is lately taken by the <hi>Turk.</hi> 11. <hi>Alten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg.</hi> 12. <hi>Tockay,</hi> both of them ſtrong by the natural ſite: and 13. <hi>Caſtel-Novo,</hi> made ſtrong by Art.</p>
            <p>Places of moſt Importance in the <hi>Turks</hi> poſſeſſion,<note place="margin">The chief Towns in the <hi>Turks</hi> part.</note> are 1. <hi>Buda,</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> called <hi>Hoffen.</hi> This City is unevenly ſeated amongſt Hills, on the South ſide of the <hi>Danow,</hi> but in the moſt fruitful part of all the Country; Its exceeding ſtrongly fortified, and adorned with many fair buildings, both private and publick; and furniſhed with ſome Medicinal Baths, which owe much of their pomp, and ſumptuouſneſs to their New Maſters, the <hi>Turks,</hi> who took it from the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 20. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1526. <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent being preſent at the taking of it. Before that time, it was the ſeat Royal of the Kings of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the chief City of the Kingdom; As now it is the ſeat of the chief <hi>Baſſa,</hi> or Lord Lieutenant for the <hi>Grand Signior.</hi> 2. <hi>Abba
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38150:4"/> Regalis,</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> called <hi>Stul-Weiſenburg,</hi> ſituated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Danow</hi> and the <hi>Dravus,</hi> ſtrongly, but unwholſomly ſeated in the midſt of an inacceſſibile Mariſh, which is joyned to the firm land by three broad Cauſeys, blocked up at the ends with three great Bulworks. But notwithſtanding its ſtrong ſituation, it was taken by the <hi>Turks, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1543. Before which time, it was the uſual place, both for the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and Interment of the Kings of <hi>Hungary.</hi> 3. <hi>Volue,</hi> on the <hi>Danow,</hi> taken in the ſame year alſo. 4. <hi>Fieſe-kirken,</hi> called in <hi>Latine Quin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Eccleſiae,</hi> from five Churches in it. A Biſhops See,<note place="margin">It was this laſt year bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned down by Count <hi>Serini.</hi>
               </note> which was taken by the <hi>Turks, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1566. and gave them a great command upon the River <hi>Dravus,</hi> upon which it is ſeated. 5 <hi>Sirmiſch,</hi> ſituated between the <hi>Danow</hi> and <hi>Savus,</hi> noted for yielding the beſt Wines, but it is a City otherwiſe of no eſtimation for the preſent, though formerly of the moſt account in all this Province, the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonia inferior:</hi> honoured with the preſence and perſonal reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of many of the Emperors, and in thoſe reſpects made the Stage of many great and memorable Actions. Here was held a Council againſt the <hi>Heretick Photinus,</hi> Biſhop of this City, who held, that Chriſt had no exiſtence of God the Father, till he was conceived, and born of the Virgin <hi>Mary, Anno Chriſti</hi> 356. 6. <hi>Zigeth,</hi> a ſtrong Town, ſituate on a Mariſh ground on the North ſide of the River <hi>Dravus,</hi> which was taken by <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1566, who there ended his Days. 7. <hi>Kereſture;</hi> nigh unto which, in the year 1596 <hi>Mahomet</hi> the third gave unto the Chriſtians ſo great an overthrow, that probably, if he had purſued his Victory, he had made a full Conqueſt of all <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi> 8. <hi>Murſa,</hi> upon the confluence of the <hi>Dravus,</hi> and the <hi>Danow.</hi> 9. <hi>Belgrade,</hi> on the confluence of the <hi>Savus</hi> and the <hi>Danow:</hi> called by the <hi>Dutch, Greek Weſſenburg:</hi> Its called <hi>Belgrad</hi> from the beautiful ſituation of it. Its hemmed in on the North with the <hi>Danow,</hi> on the Eaſt with the <hi>Savus,</hi> on the other ſides its defended with very ſtrong Walls, deep Ditches, and impregnable Ramparts. It belonged anciently to the Deſpots of <hi>Servia,</hi> by whom it was conſigned over to <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund,</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> as beſt able to keep it, the Deſpot
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38150:4"/> being ſatisfied with Lands and other Territories of a better value. Heretofore it was the Bulwork of Chriſtendom againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> who received before it many great, and notable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes, of which the moſt memorable were thoſe of <hi>Amurath</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great: It was taken at laſt (to the great loſs, and ſhame of the Chriſtian world, who relieved not the beſieged in due time) by <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1520.</p>
            <p>On the North ſide of the Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> there is, 10 <hi>Peſth,</hi> over againſt <hi>Buda,</hi> on the River <hi>Danow.</hi> 11. <hi>Vaccia,</hi> on the ſame River, a Biſhops See. 12. <hi>Colocza,</hi> an Archb ſhops See, on the ſame River alſo. 13. <hi>Zegedin,</hi> on the Weſt ſide of the River <hi>Tibiſcus.</hi> 14. <hi>Temeſwar,</hi> on the Eaſt of that Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver towards <hi>Tranſylvania:</hi> which is the ordinary reſidence of a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Baſſa. 15. <hi>Gyula,</hi> a ſtrong Town on the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Tranſylavania,</hi> which was betrayed by <hi>Nicholas Kereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> the Governor thereof, in the laſt year of <hi>Solyman,</hi> upon promiſe of a great reward: But <hi>Selimus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Solyman,</hi> cauſed him to be ſhut up in a Barrel, knocked full of nails, with the points inwards, and ſo to be tumbled up and down till he dyed moſt miſerably. On the Barrel there was this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription written: <hi>Here receive the reward of thy Covetouſneſs and Treaſon:</hi> Gyula, <hi>thou ſoldeſt for Gold. If thou beſt not faithful to</hi> Maximilian, <hi>thy Natural Lord, neither wilt thou be true to me.</hi> 16. <hi>Singidon,</hi> on the South ſide of <hi>Gyula,</hi> betwixt which, and <hi>Belgrade</hi> are the Fields of <hi>Maxon,</hi> famous for the ſlaughter of fifty thouſand <hi>Turks,</hi> ſlain here in Battel, under the prudent conduct of <hi>John Huniades:</hi> Anno 1456.</p>
            <p>The People of <hi>Hungary</hi> are ſtrong of Body,<note place="margin">The qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the People.</note> but ſomewhat rude of behaviour, reſpecting neither the Liberall Arts, nor Mechanick Trades. The greateſt aſperſion is the name of a <hi>Coward,</hi> which cannot be wiped off, without the killing of a <hi>Turk,</hi> after which they are priviledged to wear a Feather, and by the number of their Feathers to ſhew how many <hi>Turks</hi> they have ſlain in Battel. They delight in Wars, &amp; like no Trade better, deſiring rather to live upon other mens labors, then upon their own. They are extream covetous, yet they have rather a deſire, then any Art to enrich themſelves, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38150:5"/> the <hi>Dutch</hi> to ingroſs all their Trading, and to mannage ſuch Commodities as their Country yields, which is the cauſe (ſeconded by the oppreſſions of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, under whom they are) that none of them riſe to any conſiderable Wealth. And for ſuch as have lands, they grow poorer every Day then other. For though the Females be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from inheriting their Fathers Poſſeſſions (to whom they give no Portion, but new clothes on their Wedding day) yet, ſeeing the Sons do equally ſhare their Fathers eſtate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them (as ſuch who hold in <hi>Gavelkind,</hi> do here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) it muſt needs be, that by ſo many Diviſions, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſions, the greateſt Patrimony that is, will be brought to little. Both Sexes in their education are inured to hardſhip, being not ſuffered to lie in Beds till the night of their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hungarians</hi> at this day contemn eaſe, and pleaſure, and live not in Towns but as ſtrangers, with a deſign to be ſoon gone. Great men lodge their delights in their Gardens, and Baths, and care not for their Buildings, but deſire to live at large. The Common People live in Cabins, and little lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ill made.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Their Habit.</note>Their Garments are long and ſtately, their Womens Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſtraight, and cover them unto the neck; they wear upon their Gowns, long Cloaks, and they cover their Heads with Vails, or Linnen Cloth, and hide all but their eyes and noſe; and moſt of them wear Pearls, and precious ſtones. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo both men and women wear Buskins up to the calf of the Leg; they mourn a whole year for their Friends and Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folks when they die, and ſometimes two years; they ſhave their Beards, and leave nothing but their Muſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ches, which are ſometimes very long. They have a particular Language, which differs not much from the <hi>Bohemians:</hi> and they have alſo a perticular form of Letters,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonian</hi> Language.</note> yet moſt commonly they uſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Characters; they are very proud and haughty, ſtrong in War, and are better Souldiers on Horſeback th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n on Foot; they are very obedient to the Prince, and his Leiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants. In the parts adjoyning to <hi>Germany</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is moſt uſed.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38150:5"/>
            <p>The ſoil in <hi>Hungary</hi> is wonderful fruitful,<note place="margin">Their commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> yielding Corn and Fruits in great abundance: The Graſs in ſome places (as in the Iſle of <hi>Comora</hi>) exceeds the heigth of a man, which doth breed ſuch a number of Cattel, that this Country alone, is thought to be able to ſerve all <hi>Europe</hi> with fleſh: they yearly ſend into <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Sclavonia</hi> eight thouſand Oxen. They have Deer, Partridge, Pheaſant in ſuch ſuperfluity that any man that will, may kill them. The other commodities of the Country are, ſtore of Silver, Copper, Iron, Steel, Tin, Lead, Vitrial, which they ſend into divers Countries; Yea, and Gold, which they not onely find in Mines, but alſo in the Sand of ſome of their Rivers. There are alſo great ſtore of Sheep, Stags, Fallow Deer, Goates, Hares, wild Boars, Wolves, Bears, and ſuch like beaſts: Beſides Goſhawkes, and many other Birds.</p>
            <p>There is ſcarce any other Country that hath more and greater Rivers than <hi>Hungary,</hi> nor more Navigable,<note place="margin">The Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</note> nor better ſtored with Fiſh: There is the <hi>Danow,</hi> which, riſing out of <hi>Nigra Sylva,</hi> or the <hi>Schwartzen-Wald,</hi> as the <hi>Germans</hi> call it, at a little Village of <hi>Schwaben,</hi> about two <hi>Dutch</hi> Miles from the Shoars of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> paſſeth through <hi>Schwaben, Bavaria, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, Hungary,</hi> &amp;c. and runs by the Cities of <hi>Ulm, Regenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg, Paſſaw, Vienna, Rab, Buda,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Belgrade,</hi> beyond w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to be called <hi>Iſter,</hi> and receiving into its channel, from the long Tracts of the <hi>Alps,</hi> the <hi>Sarmatian,</hi> and <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains, above ſixty Navigable Rivers, beſides leſſer Brooks, diſgorgeth his full ſtomach out of ſeven Mouths into the lap of the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea: the whole length of his courſe being fifteen hundred Miles. Whence a modern Poet ſaid,
<q>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cedere</hi> Danubius <hi>ſe tibi</hi> Nile <hi>negat.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O ſeven-mouth'd <hi>Nile,</hi> I plainly ſee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Danow</hi> will ſcare give place to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Savus,</hi> which riſing in <hi>Carniola,</hi> falls into <hi>Danow.</hi> 3. <hi>Dravus,</hi> which riſes in <hi>Carinthia,</hi> and falls into <hi>Danow.</hi> 4. <hi>Tibuſcus,</hi> or the <hi>Tiſſe,</hi> which riſes in <hi>Maramufia,</hi> under
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38150:6"/> the high tops of the <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains, and abounds more with Fiſh than any other of the Rivers of <hi>Hungary:</hi> for they find in it great ſtore of Surgeons, Pikes (which ſometimes have Livers of an Ell long) Carps, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whence they uſe to ſay, that in this River two parts are water, and the third Fiſh. There are alſo many other Rivers, wherein are great ſtore of Trouts, Salmons, Perches, Lampries, Barbels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A famous Lake.</note>There is alſo a famous Lake called <hi>Balatan</hi> (by the <hi>Dutch Platſe</hi>) which is in length forty <hi>Italian</hi> Miles, but of breadth unequal: In ſome places its ten Miles broad, in others but three.<note place="margin">The Rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </note> There be alſo many Medicinal waters, and more hot Baths than any one country hath in <hi>Europe.</hi> Some waters their be of a ſtrange nature, whereof ſome falling upon the ground are turned into Stone: Others, about the Town of <hi>Smolnice,</hi> which falling into Ditches, make a kind of mud, out of which, being tried, and melted, they make very good Copper: and ſome again which flow in Winter, and freeze in Summer. And neer unto <hi>Biſtrice,</hi> or <hi>Menſol,</hi> there is a Spring or Fountain out of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> comes a green Water, whereof they make Solder for their Gold. This Country alſo abounds in Mineral Salt at <hi>Maromaruſia,</hi> and other places, which they cut like unto a ſtone. There are alſo hot waters, whoſe Fiſh being taken out, and put into cold water dies preſently. The waters of the County of <hi>Liptove,</hi> neer unto the Village of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John,</hi> are good againſt Scabs. In the Territory of <hi>Zepus</hi> there are waters in which Wood is turned into Stone: and neer unto S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Martins</hi> Church, in the ſame place, there is a water which ſeems to boil, the which turns into ſtone, both above and under ground, and this Stone is almoſt like unto the <hi>Pumeiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Country of <hi>Zolie,</hi> there is a Gulf, or breach in the ground, which caſts forth ſuch a deadly ſtink as it kills the Birds that fly over it. Neer unto <hi>Javerin</hi> upon the Banks of the River <hi>Danow,</hi> towards the Eaſt, are to be ſeen, ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of <hi>Trajans</hi> Bridge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trajans</hi> Bridge.</note> built upon that River in <hi>Moeſia,</hi> an admirable and memorable work, conſiſting of twenty Arches of ſquare ſtone, which Arches were a hundred and fifty foot high, beſides the foundation, and ſixty foot broad, and each Arch was ſeventy foot wide. Its a thing to be admired by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38150:6"/> what means, force, or Art they could build theſe ſeveral Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in this deep and violent ſtream, and lay the foundations of ſo great a burden, the bottom of the River being ſo deep of mud, and there being no means to turn the courſe of the Water, he Arches above the Water were demoliſhed by the command of <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor, but the Piles ſtand ſtill, for a Teſtimony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Poſterity, that there was nothing impoſſible to the power and wealth of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>The Principal Mountains of this Country are 1. <hi>Carpatus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</note> the <hi>Sarmatian,</hi> or <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains, ſpoken of before. 2. <hi>Matzan,</hi> neer to the City of <hi>Agria,</hi> whereon grow brave Trees in abundance. 3. <hi>Erdol,</hi> the higheſt of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Faith was firſt planted here in the time of King <hi>Steven,</hi> ſurnamed the Saint,<note place="margin">They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Chriſtian Faith.</note> being invited and perſwaded thereunto by the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, who, upon this condition, gave to this <hi>Steven</hi> in marriage his Siſter <hi>Gilla;</hi> and it was effected by the preaching and induſtry of <hi>Albert,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Prague. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1016, or thereabouts. Since which time Chriſtianity hath continued here without interruption, having been defended gallantly, and bravely againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> for a long time. But now, <hi>Mahumatiſm</hi> is much ſpread over a great part of it; by reaſon of thoſe many places which the <hi>Turks</hi> hold in it. As for the Chriſtians, ſome pertinaciouſly adhere to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> Some follow the Doctrine of <hi>Luther;</hi> and ſome that of <hi>Calvin;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions.</note> Beſides which, there are <hi>Arians, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and other <hi>Hereticks</hi> crept in amongſt them. Yet all theſe different parties agree in this, to puniſh Adultery, and Fornication with Death. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forcing his Daughter; the Husband his Wife, the Brother his Siſter, to the place of Execution.</p>
            <p>The worthieſt Schollar that ever this Kingdom produced was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Jerome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The beſt Scholars, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</note> a worthy Father of the <hi>Latine</hi> Church who was born in <hi>Stridon;</hi> and of later years, <hi>Steven Kis,</hi> ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Zegedine,</hi> from the place of his birth; and the moſt worthy of their Souldiers, were, <hi>John Huniades,</hi> who ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly reſiſted and repelled the incurſions of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and ſlew of them fifty thouſand at the Battel of <hi>Maxon;</hi> and after,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38150:7"/> him, was <hi>Matthias Corvinus,</hi> his Son, King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> of whom a Poet writes thus,
<q>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>— <hi>Patriae decus, unica ſtirpis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gloria,</hi> Pannonicae <hi>caedis fortiſſimus ult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>His Countries pride, the Glory of his Race,</l>
                     <l>Revenger of th' <hi>Hungarians</hi> late diſgrace.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>The King of <hi>Hungary</hi> Governs his Realm chiefly by two Magiſtrates; yet in the Upper <hi>Hungary</hi> there uſed to be three Magiſtrates. The firſt Governs the Realm in the Kings Name. The chief Magiſtrate is the Palatine of the Realm, who is next unto the King, and Judges the King himſelf, if he be accuſed. He is choſen by the People, and his Office is not Hereditary. There is alſo the Judge of the Court, who is one of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Judges of the Realm. Then the perpetual Chancellor, who is the Archbiſhop of <hi>Strigonium,</hi> the Primate of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Chief Secretary; His Office is to Annoint the King when he is choſen; and to Seal all Patents, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. There is alſo the Maſter of the Court, who muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity follow the King, and is his neereſt Counſellor. There is alſo the Maſter of the Royal Tavernies, who hath the charge of Mines, and Saltpits, and doth Judge of cauſes which concern the Kings revenues in Towns, Burroughs, and Caſtles.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Magiſtrate is appointed for matters of Juſtice, and this Magiſtracy comprehends three Officers of very great authority, that is, the Vice Palatine of the Realm, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Judge of the Preſence, who holds the Kings place in Judgements, and is above all other Judges, and the Vice-Judge of the Court. The Inferior Officers are thoſe, who are rather Executioners of Judgement than Magiſtrates; and there are two Protonotaries of the Perſonal Judge, one of the Vice-Palatine, and one of the Vice-Judge of the Court. All theſe are called Maſters, and have joyned to them the Archbiſhop of <hi>Strigoniums</hi> Secretary, who is called <hi>Fiſcall,</hi> beſides twelve Aſſiſtants, and certain ſworn Notaries.</p>
            <p>Beſides all theſe, there are the Kings Officers, as the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38150:7"/> the High Chamberlain, and other Chamberlains; the Lord Steward of the Kings Houſe, and other Maſters of the Houſhold; the Chief Cup-Bearer; Gentlemen Servants; Uſhers, and many other Inferior Officers.</p>
            <p>This Kingdom of <hi>Hungary</hi> hath ever been Elective,<note place="margin">Their Kingdom is Elective.</note> and hath had ſpecial Priviledges indulged them by their former Kings. King <hi>Andrew</hi> gave Authority to his Prelates, Peers, and People, that without any imputation of diſloyalty, they might contradict, oppoſe, and reſiſt their King, if he did any thing in Violation of their Laws and Sanctions: as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Heylin</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Geography.</hi> p. 189. But ſince the houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> came to poſſeſs this Crown of <hi>Hungary,</hi> they have made their Government more abſolute, and the People more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, having loſt much of their former Liberty, and Priviledges. For in their ancient Government, when as their Kings meant to undertake War, to conclude a Peace, or to alter any thing in the Government of the Commonwealth, their manner was to aſſemble the Barons, Biſhops, and Gentlemen at a certain place, where, by the conſent of the greater part, their Kings had power to confirm, abrogate, or make Laws; To denounce War, to conclude Peace, and to charge their Lands with Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and Taxes according as neceſſity required; Which Aſſemblies are ſtill in uſe, but the freedom thereof, is much retrenched, and impaired, there being now nothing propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to theſe Aſſemblies by their new Governors, but to raiſe a Contribution of Mony to reſiſt the <hi>Turk</hi> when he threatens any Invaſion, to which demand, the Eſtates give their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by a certain Day.</p>
            <p>They Judge according to Written Laws; but they have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other kind of deciding controverſies which happen amongſt them; For if the matter be difficult to end,<note place="margin">Trial by Combate.</note> they ordain that it ſhall be tryed by Combate betwixt the Parties, the which is performed in the preſence of the King or his Lieutenant, and the victory is adjudged to the ſtronger; and he is judged Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious, that doth ſo amaſe his enemy at his firſt approach, as that he retires out of the Field, or being in combate, is ſo purſued, as that he is forced to abandon the place that is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to them. They that fight on Horſeback, charge firſt with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38150:8"/> their Lances, and then they fall to it with their Swords; and for ſuch as fight on foot, they have their privy parts covered, and all the reſt of their body is naked.</p>
            <p>Only the males (as was ſaid before) inherit; and if they die without Sons, the Daughters do not ſucceed, but the Lands of the deceaſed fall by <hi>Eſcheat</hi> to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Their ſtrength.</note>The forces of this Kingdom whilſt it was entire, may beſt be Judged of, by thoſe great Armies which they have brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Field againſt the <hi>Turk:</hi> But now two parts of three of <hi>Hungary</hi> being ſubdued by the <hi>Turks,</hi> that which remains is not able to anſwer the proportion of former times.</p>
            <p>The foot Souldiers are commonly but meanly armed; the defect whereof is rather to be imputed to Prince than to the People, who can but bring their Bodies (which is all they have) for the defence of their Country. Their Horſemen (which are called <hi>Heiducks</hi>) are maintained in a continual readineſs, at the charge of the Nobility, and principal Gentry. Theſe are Couſin-Germans to the <hi>Coſſacques,</hi> almoſt as cruel, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous as they.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues.</note>The chief Revenues of this Kingdom come from the Silver Mines, out of which is yearly raiſed about a Million and an half of Guilders. But <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond, made it up two Millions by ſeizing on the Lands of the Cathedrall, and Collegiat Churches; and aſſigning annual Penſions to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Canons, and other Religious Perſons: Moſt of which ſummes come cleerly to the Emperors Coffers; the Preſidiary Souldiers being paid with Contribution Money, raiſed out of the Peoples purſes; and the Lieutenant Generals Salary, which comes to thirty thouſand Dollars by the year, is defrayed out of their purſes alſo.</p>
            <p>Not to ſpeak any thing of the firſt Inhabitants of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſo many ages ſince extinct, we will come to the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> the laſt and Principal Actors upon the Stage of this Kingdom, and the givers of the preſent Name to it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſe coming into it,<note place="margin">Called formerly <hi>Pannonia.</hi>
               </note> it was called <hi>Pannonia.</hi> Theſe <hi>Hungari</hi> were a <hi>Scythian</hi> People, firſt known in <hi>Europe</hi> by their acts in the time of the Emperor <hi>Arnulphus,</hi> when wandring in <hi>Sarmatia Europaea,</hi> they were by him called into this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38150:8"/> to aſſiſt him againſt <hi>Suantobogius,</hi> King of the <hi>Moravians,</hi> from whom they took <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and ſo much of <hi>Hungary</hi> as lies on both ſides of the River <hi>Tiſſe,</hi> inhabited at that time by the <hi>Sclaves,</hi> and ſome ſcattered remnants of the <hi>Avares,</hi> whom they killed, or forced to ſeek new habitations, planting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in thoſe places which they took from them, which is now the Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> after which they paſſed the <hi>Danow</hi> and ſubdued <hi>Pannonia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Goverment at firſt was under Dukes:<note place="margin">The firſt King.</note> But <hi>Stephen</hi> the fourth, upon his embracing the Goſpel, was honored with the title of a King, enjoyed by his ſucceſſors to this very day. In the time of <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Saint, Dalmatia,</hi> and <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atia</hi> were added to the Crown of <hi>Hungary,</hi> as bequeathed to the King by his Siſter <hi>Zelomira,</hi> the Widow of the laſt King of thoſe Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1248. Under the Raign of <hi>Bela</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade it.</note> the <hi>Tartarians,</hi> to the number of five hundred thouſand fighting men, brake into <hi>Hungary,</hi> and like a violent whirlwind, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all before them, tyrannizing here for three years together, comitting many mercileſs Maſſacres, and infinite ravages whereſoever they came. In the Raign of <hi>Steven</hi> the fourth, <hi>Myſia,</hi> and <hi>Bulgary</hi> were made Tributaries to the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Dukes, and Kings of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuſala,</hi> the firſt Duke (or Captain) of the <hi>Hungary;</hi> He ſubdued <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and the Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> and paſſed over the <hi>Danow;</hi> but was ſlain in his Wars againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who then poſſeſſed <hi>Pannonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Toxus,</hi> the next Duke, who ſubdued <hi>Pannonia,</hi> or the Lower <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Griſa,</hi> the Son of <hi>Toxus</hi> was the third Duke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen,</hi> the fourth Duke, and the firſt King of <hi>Hungary. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1000.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Almain,</hi> and Nephew of <hi>Stephen.</hi> He was depoſed by <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Bela,</hi> the Sons of <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Geiſa</hi> the firſt, and Brother of <hi>Stephen,</hi> the firſt King. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1039.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:38150:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andrew,</hi> who was the eldeſt Son of that <hi>Ladiſlaus Anno Chriſti</hi> 1047.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bela,</hi> the Brother of <hi>Andrew,</hi> ſucceeded him. <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1059.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Son of <hi>Andrew,</hi> who was expelled his Kingdom by <hi>Geiſa. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1062.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Geiſa</hi> the ſecond, the Son of <hi>Bela. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1075.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Saint,</hi> who was Brother to <hi>Geiſa</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1078.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coloman,</hi> the Son of <hi>Geiſa</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1096.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the ſecond, who was Son of <hi>Coloman. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1114.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bela</hi> the ſecond, the Nephew of <hi>Geiſa</hi> the ſecond by his Son <hi>Almus. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1132.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Geiſa</hi> the third, the Son of <hi>Bela</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1142.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the third, the Son of <hi>Geiſa</hi> the third. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1162.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bela</hi> the third, the Brother of <hi>Stephen</hi> the third. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1172.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Emaricus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Bela</hi> the third. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1191.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the ſecond, the Son of <hi>Emaricus;</hi> He Raigned but ſix Moneths being ſlain by Treaſon, when he was very young, and died without Iſſue. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1201.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andrew</hi> the ſecond, the Son of <hi>Bela</hi> the third, and Brother of <hi>Emaricus. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1201.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bela</hi> the fourth, the Son of <hi>Andrew</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1236.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the fourth, the Son of <hi>Bela</hi> the fourth. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1271.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the third, the Son of <hi>Stephen</hi> the fourth. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1273.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andrew</hi> the third, Nephew to <hi>Bela</hi> the fourth by his Brother <hi>Stephen. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1290.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Martel,</hi> the Son of <hi>Charles,</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> by <hi>Mary</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Stephen</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourth, againſt whom was choſen <hi>Wenceſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Son of King <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Anne</hi> his Wife, who was the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38150:9"/> Daughter of <hi>Bela</hi> the fourth; and after three years, <hi>Otho</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> deſcended from <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> another of the Daughters of <hi>Bela</hi> the fourth, was choſen alſo by a Faction againſt <hi>Wenceſlaus:</hi> But <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> ſurrending his title to <hi>Otho,</hi> and <hi>Otho</hi> being not long after forced to ſurrender his title, <hi>Charles Martel</hi> remained King of <hi>Hungary. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1302.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lodovicus,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Charles Martel</hi> by his Son <hi>Carlco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> ſucceeded not only in the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> but of <hi>Poland</hi> alſo, in the right of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Mother, Siſter of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimir</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1343.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Naples,</hi> deſcended from <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Stephen</hi> the fourth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, by their Son, <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Durazzo,</hi> one of the younger Brothers of <hi>Charles Martel,</hi> which <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, after a ſhort raign, was poiſoned by the Widow of the former King to make way for her Daughters coming to the Crown. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1383.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Luxenbourg,</hi> was choſen King of <hi>Hungary</hi> in right of <hi>Mary</hi> his Wife, who was the youngeſt Daughter of <hi>Lodovicus. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1387.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albert</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> Emperor, and King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> in right of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife, the Daughter of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmund. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1438.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Jugello,</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> ſucceeded in the minority of <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Albert,</hi> he was unhappily ſlain at the Battel of <hi>Varna</hi> againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> together with thirty thouſand of his men. He had made, and ſworn a truce with the <hi>Turk;</hi> But the Popes Legate, upon a ſeeming advantage, perſwaded him to break it, and abſolved him from his Oath; and when they came to the Battel, the Chriſtians at firſt had the better: Whereupon <hi>Amurath</hi> the ſecond, againſt whom they fought, drew the writing out of his boſome, and with his eyes lift up to Heaven, he deſired Chriſt to look upon the perfidious dealing, wherewith his followers diſhonoured him; and ſo encouraging his men, he obtained the Victory. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1440.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the fifth, the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Son of <hi>Albert</hi> by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38150:10"/> 
                  <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> ſucceeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1444.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthias Corvinus,</hi> the Son of the famous <hi>Huniades,</hi> after the Death of <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the fifth, was choſen King of <hi>Hungary. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1458.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> the ſecond, or <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the ſixth, the Son of <hi>Caſimir</hi> the fourth, of <hi>Poland,</hi> and of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Albert;</hi> ſucceeded in the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1491.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ludovicus</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who in the one and twentieth year of his age, and the tenth of his Raign, was drawn into the Field againſt <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, the Battel was fought at a Village, called <hi>Mugace,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and <hi>Buda,</hi> in which nineteen thouſand <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians</hi> were ſlain, and the young King drowned in his flight. <hi>Lewis</hi> thus dead, <hi>John de Sepuſio,</hi> Vayvod of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> was by the States choſen King of <hi>Hungary;</hi> But <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> Archduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> chalenged the Kingdom, in the right of <hi>Anne</hi> his Wife, who was Daughter and ſiſter to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus,</hi> and <hi>Lewis,</hi> Kings of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia.</hi> On this prentence he invaded the Kingdom, and drove out <hi>John,</hi> who to recover his right, called in <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent, who took ſuch faſt footing in <hi>Hungary,</hi> that his ſucceſſors could never ſince be removed. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1571.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John de Sepuſio,</hi> Vayvod of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> and King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1527.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> Brother to the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, was Elected King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in reſpect to <hi>Anne</hi> his Wife, Siſter of <hi>Ludovicus</hi> the ſecond, and in the ſame right, laid claim to the Crown of <hi>Hungary,</hi> whereunto he was choſen by a party prepared for him; but upon the Death of <hi>John de Sepu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio,</hi> he was received by all. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1540.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maximilian,</hi> the Emperor, was King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and Archduke of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> He was the Son of <hi>Ferdinand, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1562.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rodulphus</hi> his Son ſucceeded him in all. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1572.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthias,</hi> the Brother of <hi>Rodulphus</hi> ſucceeded him. <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1608.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:38150:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, of <hi>Gratz,</hi> next heir to <hi>Matthias</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> intruded, againſt whom the <hi>Hungarians</hi> called in <hi>Bethlem Gabor,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> whom they Elected for their King; But upon the Emperors great ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> againſt <hi>Frederick,</hi> Prince Elector Palatine, <hi>Gabor</hi> relinquiſhed his right, and hearkned to a Peace. <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1618.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third, the Son of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, was choſen and Crowned King of <hi>Hungary</hi> in the Life of his Father. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1637. And ſucceeded him in the Empire, and Kingdom of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the fourth, the Son of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third, was Crowned King of <hi>Hungary</hi> in his Fathers life time. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1646. And died before his Father. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1653. being but two and twenty years old.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leopold Ignatius,</hi> his Brother, the Son of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third, was alſo Crowned King of <hi>Hungary</hi> in his Fathers life time. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1653. and is now living.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An account of the Controverſies which have happened in the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſince the Peace that was made with the <hi>Turks. Anno Chriſti 1605, to 1663.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The controverſies which happened in <hi>Hungary,</hi> as well for Religion, as for the charges, and Commands in Armies, were the cauſes of many, and great miſchiefs. For <hi>Botzkay Iſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Duke of <hi>Kiſmaria,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> revolted from the Emperor, having drawn many Noble men of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> to joyn with him upon aſſurance of aſſiſtance from the <hi>Turk;</hi> Then did <hi>Botzkay</hi> take the field with great numbers of <hi>Heiducks,</hi> and made a Declaration againſt the Emperors Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, which were four, who joyning their Forces together, went againſt <hi>Botzkay.</hi> When the Armies met, the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> both Horſe and Foot yielded to <hi>Botzkay;</hi> The fight continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſix hours, and the Imperialiſts were routed, <hi>Belliceuſe,</hi> one of their Generals, fled, and the <hi>Germans,</hi> and <hi>Sileſians</hi> were cut in pieces; <hi>Pets,</hi> and <hi>Pallas Lippay,</hi> were taken Priſoners, and <hi>Botzkay</hi> ſent <hi>Pets,</hi> and ſome Enſigns to <hi>Herder Baſſa,</hi> to ſhew his affection to the <hi>Turk:</hi> and <hi>Pallas Lippay</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:38150:11"/> remained Lieutenant to <hi>Botzkay:</hi> and they publiſhed another Declaration, that they took up Arms for their Civil Liberties, and Conſciences, and to hinder the Perſecution of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Hereupon the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy, &amp; Jeſuites were forced to fly to <hi>Vienna;</hi> and the Citizens of <hi>Caſſovia</hi> thruſt the Prieſts and Clergy out of their Towns, and became Proteſtants of the <hi>Auguſtane</hi> Confeſſion. <hi>Baſte,</hi> the Emperors Lieutenant, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a General Pardon in his Maſters name, but it prevailed nothing; He alſo beſieged <hi>Caſſovia</hi> in vain, the Gariſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of ſix thouſand men. Having raiſed his Siege, in his return, he took <hi>Epper,</hi> and ſome weaker places, upon condition to ſuffer them to enjoy their Religion according to the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Ausbourg:</hi> But being purſued by <hi>Botzkay,</hi> he loſt thirty Waggons laden with Silver, and ſtore of Clothes that came from <hi>Vienna.</hi> This ſo amazed the neighbour places, that the <hi>Germans,</hi> and other Strangers were cut in pieces.</p>
               <p>Then did <hi>Baſte</hi> perſwade <hi>Botzkay</hi> by his letters, to hearken to peace, and to draw the Emperors Subjects to their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: <hi>Botzkay</hi> anſwered, that he was content, upon condition that he ſhould enjoy the Principality of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and be the Emperors Lieutenant in <hi>Hungary.</hi> That the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Walloons</hi> ſhould depart the Country: That the Souldiers ſhould be paid; That the Proteſtants ſhould not be moleſted in the exerciſe of their Religion: That <hi>Belliceuſe</hi> (who was the cauſe of theſe troubles) ſhould be delivered into his hands to do juſtice upon him; and that the Emperor ſhould come in Perſon to the Eſtates at <hi>Ponſon,</hi> and in the mean time the <hi>Germans</hi> ſhould not ſtir out of the Gariſons to plunder the Countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſte</hi> ſeeing theſe demands ſo high, returned no anſwer. All <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> obeyed <hi>Botzkay;</hi> and he received Money from the <hi>Turk,</hi> wherewith he paid his Souldiers, and called the Eſtates of <hi>Hungary</hi> to a General Aſſembly upon the laſt of <hi>April.</hi> In the mean time the Earls of <hi>Herin, Nadaſte,</hi> and <hi>Buda,</hi> who before had fought with the <hi>Turk,</hi> fell to <hi>Botzkays</hi> Party, having an Army of twenty five thouſand men; <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovia,</hi> and <hi>Wallachia</hi> alſo obeyed him. This made <hi>Matthias</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:38150:11"/> the Archduke, in the Emperors name, to ſeek for peace; and <hi>Botzkay</hi> ſent <hi>Helias Hali,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Helias Hasky.</note> who met with the Emperors Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, and told him that his Maſter would not refuſe Peace if the Emperor would grant him the Conditions which he had before propounded; as alſo that no Biſhop ſhould be of the Senate in <hi>Hungary,</hi> but he onely that was Chancellor.</p>
               <p>Then did <hi>Botzkay</hi> ſend Ambaſſadors to <hi>Vienna,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Peace conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> where at laſt a Peace was concluded in the year 1606, and the Moneth of <hi>September,</hi> which conſiſted of theſe ſix Articles.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">The Arti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror.</note> That they ſhould enjoy liberty of Conſcience through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all <hi>Hungary,</hi> namely the <hi>Catholicks, Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniſts,</hi> and that no other Religion ſhould be tollerated.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Archduke <hi>Matthias</hi> ſhould be Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral for the Emperor through all <hi>Hungary,</hi> and that all things ſhould remain in the ſame eſtate as they were in for the preſent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That <hi>Botzkay</hi> ſhould continue Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> Earl of <hi>Sicules,</hi> and Palatine of high <hi>Hungary,</hi> and for want of Heirs Male, all ſhould revert to the Emperor, and that <hi>Botz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kays</hi> Daughters ſhould be married according to their quality at the Emperors charge.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That from thence-forth the Palatine, and the General Treaſurers ſhould be choſen by the Eſtates of the Country.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That a General pardon ſhould be publiſhed, to the end that all matters might be forgotten on both parts.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Chambers and New Courts to be aboliſhed; the <hi>Hungarians</hi> to redeem the Caſtles pawned to the <hi>Germans;</hi> the Government of the Kingdom to be adminiſtred by the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> only <hi>Raab,</hi> and <hi>Comorra</hi> may be Governed by deſerving <hi>Germans;</hi> and that Biſhops deſcended of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to have voice and place in Council, others not. Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires were made at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and all other Places for this happy Peace.</p>
               <p>Shortly after alſo a Peace was concluded between the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and the Great <hi>Turk</hi> for twenty years,<note place="margin">The Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles with the Great <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </note> whereof theſe were the Articles.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That every one ſhould return into his Poſſeſſions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edifie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38150:12"/> his Houſes and Caſtles, and remain in the ſame Eſtate that he was in before the War.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Emperor ſhould be called Father, and the <hi>Turk</hi> Son; which titles they ſhould give each to other by their Ambaſſadors, and in their Writing ſhould uſe the word Emperor, and not King.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Tarters</hi> ſhould be comprehended in this Peace, with a prohibition not to make any ſpoil in the Emperors Country, nor in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That all the Signiories belonging to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> ſhould be comprehended in this Peace.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That all Acts of Hoſtility ſhould ceaſe, and tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be puniſhed by exemplary Juſtice.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That neither Part ſhall ſurpriſe any Fort, Town, Houſe, nor take any Priſoner, nor ſend any Spy into <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. That the Treaty of Peace made with <hi>Botzkay</hi> ſhould be truly obſerved.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That Merchants might paſs and Traffique freely through their Countries; and that there ſhould be four or five Fairs in every year in ſuch places as ſhould be appointed.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That the Baſſa of <hi>Buda,</hi> the Governour of <hi>Javerin,</hi> and the Governour of <hi>Sclavonia</hi> ſhall have Authority to pacifie all factions, and diviſions that may ariſe, and if they were of importance, the Emperor and great <hi>Turk</hi> ſhould be Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatours.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That all Priſoners ſhall be ſet at liberty according to their quality.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That the Archduke ſhall ſend an Ambaſſador with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Vizier, and the Vizier <hi>Amurath</hi> ſhall ſend a Preſent to the Archduke <hi>Matthias,</hi> and the Emperor ſhall ſend a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of two hundred thouſand <hi>Florins</hi> to the Great <hi>Turk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. That the Great <hi>Turk</hi> ſhall ſend another to him of the like valew.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That this Peace ſhall continue firm for twenty years, and they ſhall every three years ſend Ambaſſadors one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other with rich Preſents.</p>
               <p n="14">14. That it ſhall be lawfull for them of either Part to ſue for debts, and they ſhall enjoy all Priviledges,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38150:12"/> and immunities, as before the War.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That <hi>Vactia</hi> ſhall remain to the Emperor, and <hi>Gran</hi> to the <hi>Turk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Baſſa of <hi>Buda</hi> treated the Chriſtians with great Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, giving to each of them rich Preſents. There was great joy at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and in the Emperors Countries for this Peace.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Botzkay</hi> dying ſhortly after,<note place="margin">New troubles.</note> cauſed great alterations in theſe Provinces; and the Peace was ill obſerved in <hi>Hungary</hi> by reaſon of the Roads that were made by the Imperialiſts and others; To prevent which, there was an Aſſembly called of all the Nobility of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> who deſired that their King might reſide in <hi>Hungary,</hi> that his preſence might ſuppreſs theſe combuſtions; and the Archduke <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> not coming within ſeven days, they made a Proteſtation againſt him for not coming, and ſo departed to their homes. The Noble men of Upper <hi>Hungary</hi> held another Aſſembly at <hi>Caſſovia, October</hi> the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, where they reſolved, that <hi>Hungary</hi> ſhould not be divided from <hi>Tranſylvania.</hi> But the <hi>Heiducks</hi> being diſcontented notwithſtanding theſe Aſſemblies, did not forbear their ravaging; they took divers Caſtles, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared themſelves Friends to the <hi>Turk,</hi> and enemies to the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and <hi>Walloons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then came the Archduke <hi>Matthias</hi> to <hi>Presbourg;</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Javerin,</hi> and all the Nobility were there to receive him. The Cardinal Archbiſhop of <hi>Gran</hi> arrived alſo, and <hi>Helias Hasky,</hi> with many Deputies from High <hi>Hungary;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> the Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment began, <hi>Jan.</hi> 23. 1608. The Cardinal and the Clergy would have moderated the Peace made with <hi>Botzkay,</hi> but <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias Hasky,</hi> with the Deputies of Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> oppoſed it, ſaying, that this Aſſembly was called onely to ſuppreſs the <hi>Heiducks;</hi> the Archdukes Deputies propoſed that there might be a League Offenſive, and Defenſive; and ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention aroſe betwixt the Clergy and Nobles, but at laſt it was pacified, and concluded that they ſhould not alter any thing in the peace made at <hi>Vienna;</hi> and that the ſaid League ſhould be made betwixt the Eſtates and the Country. As for the diſcontented <hi>Heiducks, Helias Hasky,</hi> and <hi>Turſo</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38150:13"/> took to go to them, and either to pacifie them, or to proclaim War againſt them.</p>
               <p>Then did the <hi>Archduke</hi> return to <hi>Vienna,</hi> where he called an Aſſembly of the Eſtates and acquainted them wich what had been done at <hi>Presbourg,</hi> intreating them to provide mony in caſe the <hi>Heiducks</hi> did not lay down Arms; He alſo aſpired to be King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and to further his deſigns, he reſolved to ſettle peace, as well with the <hi>Heyducks</hi> as with the <hi>Turk;</hi> and <hi>Hasky</hi> and <hi>Turſo</hi> ſo far prevailed with the <hi>Hyducks</hi> that fifteen Troops of them entred into their pay, and the reſt were diſperſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the Emperor to make him King of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </note>Preſently after did the Archduke raiſe an Army of twenty Thouſand old Souldiers, with which he marched through <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia</hi> into <hi>Bohemia</hi> towards the Emperor, his Brother, who was at <hi>Prague,</hi> and there he enforced him to reſign the Crown of <hi>Hungary</hi> to him, and to diſcharge the <hi>Hungarians</hi> from their Oath, who ſhould chooſe him King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly the Crown of <hi>Hungary,</hi> with other marks of Royalty were ſent out of <hi>Prague,</hi> and againſt they came, the Archduke put his Army into Battalia to receive them. There were brought to him the Sword of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> he Golden Ball, the Buskins, the Antique Roab, and the Royal Scepter; the Archduke, attended wich many Noble men, went forth to meet them. All the Ordinance was ſhot off thrice, and the Souldiers diſcharged their pieces as oft.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being thus diſpatched, the Siege before <hi>Prague</hi> was raiſed, and the Archduke, dividing his Army into three parts,<note place="margin">He comes back to <hi>Vienna.</hi>
                  </note> retired to <hi>Vienna;</hi> and when he came thither, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants went forth to meet him <hi>July</hi> 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, and made him an entry, as to their Soveraign Lord.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time there came to <hi>Vienna</hi> an Ambaſſador from the <hi>Turk,</hi> ſent by the Baſſa of <hi>Buda,</hi> for a confirmation of the Peace, before concluded, and with rich Preſents, <hi>Octob.</hi> 22. The Archduke parted from <hi>Vienna,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">He goes to <hi>Presbourg.</hi>
                  </note> and came to <hi>Presbourg,</hi> were he was received with great Pomp by the Noble men of <hi>Hungary</hi> there being ten thouſand men at Arms. <hi>Nov.</hi> 6. they preſented to him the Articles, conformable to the Edict of Pacification made in the year 1606, whereof you have an account before.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:38150:13"/>
               <p>Theſe Article being preſented to King <hi>Matthias</hi> (for ſo now we muſt call him) he confirmed them, and choſe <hi>Helias Hasky</hi> Palatine; and then was he Proclaimed King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary, Novemb.</hi> 14.<note place="margin">His Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> and upon the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Day he was Annointed and Crowned in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Martins</hi> Church in <hi>Presburg,</hi> whereof theſe were the Ceremonies, which I have ſet down to pleaſe the Reader.</p>
               <p>The Crown was brought upon a Royal Chariot from the Caſtle to the Church, with ten Enſigns,<note place="margin">The Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of it.</note> it being in a little Coffer covered with Cloath of Gold, and then put into the Veſtry. Four of the Chief Senators, were at the four Corners of the Chariot, and the other Senators and Chief Noble men followed it. The King being attired after the <hi>Hungarian</hi> manner, mounted upon an Horſe with a rich Capariſon, and accompanied by his Brother, the Archduke, and many other Noble men of divers Nations, came unto the ſaid Church, where having ſtaid a little in the Veſtry, two Biſhops came to conduct him to the Altar, and before him there went ten Noblemen carrying the ten Enſigns, and five others followed them, whereof the firſt carried the Croſs, the ſecond the Pix, the third the Royal Sword, the fourth the Scepter, and the fifth, which was <hi>Helias Hasky,</hi> the Crown. Cardinal <hi>Fortgaſi</hi> did the Office, being aſſiſted by many Biſhops and Prelates, who Annointed the King when the Maſs began, and ſet the Crown upon his Head whilſt the Goſpel was reading, all the People crying with one voice, <hi>God ſave the King of</hi> Hungary.</p>
               <p>Maſs being ended, the King took the Royal Sword, which <hi>Colonita,</hi> the Marſhal of <hi>Hungary</hi> held, and layd it thrice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Clergy in the form of a Croſs: then received he the Communion at the hands of the ſaid Cardinal: After which they caſt a larges of Gold and Silver amongſt the People. Which done, the King went by a Gallery from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Martins</hi> Church to another called the <hi>Deſchauſſes,</hi> where, after they had read the Goſpel, he made two and twenty Knights; Then being attired in his Royal Ornaments, and the Crown upon his Head, he went to Horſe, and was brought to a bank of Earth, which he leaped thrice over, and then he flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Sword thrice in the air in form of a Croſs; which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38150:14"/> done, he returned to the Caſtle where the Feaſt was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</note>The Ceremonies being over, he was forced to deprive the <hi>Germans</hi> of the Dignities, Charges, Eſtates, and Offices which they held in <hi>Hungary;</hi> and ſo having pacified the Country, and reduced under his Crown that which the Chriſtians held there, he returned to <hi>Vienna.</hi> Thus in the ſpace of ſeven Moneths he cauſed himſelf to be Crowned King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and to be acknowleged Archduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and Marqueſs of <hi>Moravia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Botzkay,</hi> a little before his Death, declared <hi>Valentine Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monnai,</hi> for Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania;</hi> But the <hi>Tranſylvanians</hi> (not pleaſed therewith) choſe <hi>Sigiſmund Rakoczi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rakoczi</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania.</hi>
                  </note> who was very deſirous to have evaded it; but they forced him to <hi>Clauſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> and made him aſſume the Principality, the <hi>Turk</hi> alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting and confirming him therein.</p>
               <p>About this time <hi>Matthias,</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> held a Diet at <hi>Caſſovia,</hi> where <hi>Sigiſmund Rakoczi,</hi> as Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> did him Fealty, and ſoon after reſigned the Principality to <hi>Gabriel Bathori,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">He reſigns to <hi>Bathori.</hi>
                  </note> wherein he ſhewed his great modeſty in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining the Soveraignty, and transfering it to an other, when he was ſo beloved and honoured by the People.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Jeſuits wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note>Shortly after (by the inſtigation of the Jeſuites) <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> infringed and invaded the <hi>Hungarians</hi> liberties about their Religion; but the Electors of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes arming themſelves in their behalf, overruled <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> whereby they were ſuffered to live in Peace.</p>
               <p>Then did <hi>Radulo,</hi> the <hi>Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Walachia,</hi> refuſe Homage to <hi>Bathori,</hi> whereupon he raiſed a very great Army, and it came to a Battel betwixt them, wherein <hi>Bathori</hi> was totally routed, and forced to fly into the Mountains. <hi>Matthias</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> taking advantage of this his overthrow, ſeized upon <hi>Clauſenburge,</hi> and ſome other ſtrong Holds that belonged to <hi>Bathori;</hi> yet ſhortly after, <hi>Bathori</hi> raiſing a new Army, beat the Kings General out of his Dominions, and forced him to hide himſelf in the Woods of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> after he had ſuffered very great extremities: yet <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> was by the Great <hi>Turk</hi> made Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> which ſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38150:14"/> enraged <hi>Bathori,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bathori</hi> murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> that he committed great ravages amongſt the People, and at laſt being forced to fly from <hi>Clauſenburg</hi> to <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radine,</hi> he was there murthered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bethlehem</hi> was immediately owned by the <hi>Tranſylvanians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds.</note> and confirmed by the Great <hi>Turk,</hi> and <hi>Matthias,</hi> who was now Emperor, his Brother <hi>Rodulphus</hi> being dead, ſhortly after died alſo, leaving his Crown to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, who the next year, was Crowned King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> at which time three Suns appeared in the Heavens, portending the Wars and miſchiefs which ſhortly after enſued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> after his Coronation, being excited thereto by the Jeſuites, brake the Articles of Peace made with <hi>Botzcai,</hi> and recalled the Jeſuites in hatred to the Proteſtants; Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after alſo, the States of <hi>Bohemia</hi> being wronged by him in their liberties both Civil, and Religious,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Frederick,</hi> choſen King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
                  </note> conferred the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom upon <hi>Frederick,</hi> Prince Elector Palatine, the Iſſue whereof is ſo well known to all, that I need ſay nothing of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1624. <hi>Ferdinand Erneſtus,</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, in his Fathers life time, was Crowned King of <hi>Hungary</hi> at <hi>Ovarum;</hi> and at the ſame time <hi>Bethlehem Gabor</hi> married <hi>Catherine,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>John Sigiſmund,</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> at <hi>Alba Julia;</hi> and 1626, <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> advanced with an Army into <hi>Hungary</hi> to joyn with Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Saxon Weymar;</hi> but hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that forty thouſand <hi>Tartars,</hi> his Confederates, were ſlain in <hi>Poland,</hi> he made peace with <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and retreated into <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and not long after dyed;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gabor</hi> dies</note> whereby all the places granted to him in <hi>Hungary,</hi> reverted to the King.</p>
               <p>After the Death of <hi>Gabor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rakoczi</hi> choſen Prince of <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>George Rakoczi</hi> was made Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> by the Election of the People, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in it by the <hi>Turk:</hi> At which time the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> ſent <hi>Esterhaſius,</hi> the Palatine of <hi>Hungary,</hi> with a great Army to poſſeſs himſelf of <hi>Tranſylvania:</hi> but <hi>Rakoczi</hi> being now ſetled, ſent an Army into <hi>Hungary</hi> that met with <hi>Eſterhaſius</hi> and overthrew him, and took ſeverall Cities: the <hi>Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> alſo ſent him ten Thouſand men in teſtimony of his affection to him, who waſted the Countrey all about
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38150:15"/> yet the Emperor, not willing to fall out with the <hi>Turk,</hi> ſat ſtill.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ferdinand de Gratz</hi> dies. Jeſuites wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1636. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond died, and left all his Dominions to his Son <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third, which change, probably, would have brought Peace to <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Tranſylvania:</hi> but the Jeſuites wrought new troubles; and the Catholick Nobles of <hi>Hungary</hi> grutched that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, by the late Wars, had procured ſome things in favour of their Religion, and the <hi>Lutherans</hi> had built a very beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Church in <hi>Presburg:</hi> The Emperor incenſed hereat, ſent to prohibite them, and diſallowed his former conceſſions. The Proteſtants hereupon had recourſe to <hi>Rakoczi,</hi> who was offended with the Emperor upon this account; There was found at <hi>Varadin</hi> in the Vault of <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> and <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> ſome Treaſure, together with a Crown, Scepter, and Jewels, one being a Diamond of a vaſt bigneſs that ſhone like a Torch, there being a curſe added to any that ſhould preſume to meddle with them till ſome extream neceſſity ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it: Theſe <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſent for, and <hi>Rakoczi</hi> refuſed to deliver them; Another thing that widened the difference was this; Some <hi>Hungarian</hi> Nobles turned Catholicks, and others that were ſuch, got Lordſhips where the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was profeſſed, and theſe took upon them to reſtrain them from the exerciſe of their Religion, and took their Churches from them, and placed Prieſts in them.</p>
               <p>Theſe irregularities <hi>Rakoczi</hi> complained of to the Emperor; deſiring him to remove them, and to obſerve thoſe immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and priviledges which he, and the Eſtates had confirmed to the Proteſtants: and whereas the Emperor had cauſed three hundred of the Proteſtant Churches to be ſhut up, he deſired that they might be reſtored to them: But the Emperor ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and put him off with delays: Hereupon <hi>Rakoczi</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed open War againſt the Emperor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rakoczi</hi> proclaims War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Emperor.</note> raiſed an Army of ſeventy thouſand, with which he invaded <hi>Hungary,</hi> publiſhing a <hi>Manifesto</hi> to juſtifie his proceedings: He took in divers Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and forced <hi>Caſſovia</hi> to a ſurrender.</p>
               <p>To ſtop his Progreſs, the Emperor ſent an Army of twenty thouſand men under Count <hi>Bucaine,</hi> but the <hi>Hungarians</hi> daily falling to <hi>Rakoczi,</hi> the other did little or nothing; In the mean
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38150:15"/> time <hi>Rakoczi</hi> beſieged and took in <hi>Tyrnaw,</hi> where,<note place="margin">He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers.</note> at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Proteſtant Preacher, he uſed much clemency to the Popiſhs Biſhop, and Noblemer.<note place="margin">Peace made.</note> But at laſt a Peace was concluded betwixt him and the Emperor, wherein ſeven Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips in <hi>Hungary</hi> were ſetled upon <hi>Rakoczi,</hi> ninety Churches were reſtored to the Proteſtants, and the reſt of their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges were confirmed to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1646,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ferdinand</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga y.</hi> His death.</note> 
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the fourth in his Fathers life time, was crowned King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and in the year 1648, Prince <hi>Rakoczi</hi> died, and was ſucceeded by his young Son <hi>George Rakoczi;</hi> and in the year 1653, King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the fourth died, having been Crowned King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> being but two and twenty years old, leaving all his Dignities, and Dominions to his Brother <hi>Leopold Ignatius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1656, the King of <hi>Sweden, Charolus Adolphus,</hi> having invaded <hi>Poland,</hi> and Conquered much of it, invited Prince <hi>Rakoczi</hi> to his Aſſiſtance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rakoczi</hi> goes into <hi>Poland.</hi>
                  </note> who entring into Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy with him, raiſed a great Army, with which he entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Poland,</hi> where he made great ſpoils, beating down the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages in Churches, out of an hatred to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion: At laſt he joyned with the <hi>Swede,</hi> and both of them beſiged <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covia,</hi> which, after a ſhort defence, was ſurrendred to them; they deſtroyed moſt of the City of <hi>Caſimer,</hi> which ſtood on the other ſide of the <hi>Weyſel:</hi> and in <hi>Lituania</hi> they took in the ſtrong City of <hi>Biſcea.</hi> But the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> at this time falling into ſome of the <hi>Swedes</hi> Countries, and the Duke of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> alſo renouncing the Kings Intereſt, the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was faign to retreat out of <hi>Poland</hi> to look to his own home, and thereby <hi>Rakoczi</hi> was left in the lurch.<note place="margin">He is deſerted.</note> The King of <hi>Poland</hi> in the mean time by his Ambaſſador at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> having bribed ſome of the Chief Officers, procured a Command from the <hi>Great Turk</hi> to <hi>Rakoczi</hi> to return into his own Country: He had alſo made a League with the Emperor, who ſent him ſixteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men to aſſiſt him againſt the <hi>Tranſylvanian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe conſiderations moved <hi>Rakoczi</hi> to ſend to the King of <hi>Poland</hi> for Peace; but he returned delatory anſwers till they had hemmed in the <hi>Tranſylvanians,</hi> that there was no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38150:16"/> for their eſcape but by fighting their way through them; which accordingly they did,<note place="margin">His return</note> and ſo retired into their own Country.</p>
               <p>This ſame year 1657, died the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ignatius Leopold</hi> made Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror.</note> leaving two Sons behind him, <hi>Ignatius Leopoldus,</hi> and <hi>Charles Joſeph;</hi> the Elder ſucceeded in the Empire, though with much regreat, becauſe he was but ſeventeen years old; and by their <hi>Golden Bull,</hi> and Cuſtome, none ſhould be choſen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eighteen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rakoczi</hi> oppoſed by the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </note>Prince <hi>Rakoczi</hi> being returned into his own Country, a <hi>Chiaux</hi> from the <hi>Great Turk</hi> met him, and commanded him to reſign his Principality to one <hi>Radus;</hi> but he delayed to do it, and ſought to ſtrengthen himſelf by the help of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Princes, who yet forſook him, all but the Princes of <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovia,</hi> and <hi>Walachia,</hi> But the <hi>Turk</hi> meeting with troubles at home, ſuffered him to be quiet for the preſent; yet the next year he ſent an Army againſt him through <hi>Walachia,</hi> againſt which the <hi>Vayvod</hi> oppoſing himſelf, was totally routed by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and forced with rich Preſents, and large promiſe of Hoſtility againſt <hi>Rakoczi,</hi> to make his Peace.</p>
               <p>Soon after the Baſſa of <hi>Buda</hi> was commanded upon the ſame ſervice, who marching into <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> attempted the taking of <hi>Arad,</hi> but the <hi>Tranſylvanian</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> Forces, being neer, took advantage of ſome confuſion amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> at their firſt coming, ſet upon them, and with their great Guns ſo ſhatered them, that they were forced to fly, and leave their Camp, many of them periſhing in the River <hi>Mur.</hi> Here were taken ſome of their Chief Officers; which ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed the <hi>Great Turk</hi> that he threatened to flea the Baſſa of <hi>Buda</hi> unleſs he preſently brought him the Head of <hi>Rakoczi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1660, the <hi>Turk</hi> ſent greater Forces into <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and Prince <hi>Rakoczi</hi> encountered them at <hi>Hermanſtadt,</hi> and he behaved himſelf very Valiantly, killing ſeventeen men with his own hands, whereupon the <hi>Turks</hi> were routed, and left the Victory to the <hi>Tranſylvanians,</hi> about ſeven Thouſand of them being ſlain upon the Place; and Prince <hi>Rakoczi</hi> in their purſuit, received five wounds,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38150:16"/> and five days after, being brought to <hi>Great Waradin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rakoczi</hi> dies.</note> he there died.</p>
               <p>His death gave great advantage, and encouragment to the <hi>Turks,</hi> who with renewed forces ſo preſſed upon the <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanians,</hi> that they were forced to betake themſelves to their ſtrong holds: whereupon General <hi>Souches</hi> had order from <hi>Vienna</hi> to march into <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and defend it againſt the <hi>Turks;</hi> This he did, and poſſeſſed himſelf of ſome ſtrong places. In <hi>July</hi> this year, the <hi>Turk,</hi> with one hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, beſieged <hi>Great Waradin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Waradine</hi> beſieged.</note> which was bravely defended by the Governour, Collonel <hi>Gaude,</hi> a <hi>Scotchman,</hi> but in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> that Gallant man was ſlain by an unhappy ſhot, which ſo diſcouraged the City, that being without hope of relief, they ſurrendred it upon Tearms, being a paſſage into <hi>Tranſylvania, Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rakoczi</hi> being dead,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Radus</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania.</hi>
                  </note> and his Couſin <hi>Radus</hi> diſliked by the <hi>Turk,</hi> there was one <hi>Barckay</hi> that made himſelf Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and was aſſiſted by the <hi>Turk,</hi> by which means he took in ſome places, pretending that he would reſign them to the Emperor, though it proved otherwiſe. About this time there appeared a Comet with the Head towards <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Comet.</note> and the tail towards <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> which ſeemed to Portend the great evils and miſchiefes that did enſue.</p>
               <p>The right ſucceſſor of <hi>Rakoczi</hi> was <hi>Remini Janos,</hi> who was owned by many of the <hi>Tranſylvanians,</hi> but ſtrongly oppoſed by <hi>Barckay,</hi> and the <hi>Turks.</hi> Yet <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1661, he fought with them at <hi>Thaſſabat,</hi> and made a great ſlaughter of them; but at laſt, being oppreſſed with numbers, he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to leave the Country.</p>
               <p>The Emperor perceiving that the <hi>Turks</hi> had a deſign upon <hi>Hungary,</hi> he raiſed an Army, ſending part of it into <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania,</hi> and at that time Count <hi>Nicholas Serini</hi> raiſed a ſtrong Fort over againſt <hi>Caniſia,</hi> or <hi>Chaniſcha,</hi> naming it <hi>Serinſwar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serinſwar</hi> built.</note> which ſo provoked the <hi>Turk</hi> that he demanded that the Fort ſhould be demoliſhed, that <hi>Serini</hi> ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> left to him: This made the Chriſtians to underſtand his meaning and to look to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:38150:17"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </note>In the mean time the <hi>Turk</hi> raiſed a mighty Army, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided an anſwerable proportion of Victuals, Ammunition, and Artillery; and the Emperor had in <hi>Hungary</hi> an Army of thirty eight thouſand <hi>Germans,</hi> whom the <hi>Hungarians</hi> favored not by reaſon of their difference in Religion, ſo that by <hi>October,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders away</note> through want of accommodations, and by ſurfeits w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they took through immoderate drinking of Wine, &amp; eating of Fruits, it mouldred almoſt to nothing; and being advanced as far as <hi>Clauſenburg</hi> in <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> they were diſtreſſed for want of Victuals and Forrage, and almoſt environed with their enemies: About this time <hi>Barckay</hi> fell into diſgrace with the <hi>Turk,</hi> who preferred <hi>Apaffi</hi> to be Prince of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apaffi</hi> made Prince of <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania.</hi>
                  </note> againſt whom <hi>Remini Janos</hi> oppoſed himſelf with eight thouſand men, but he went daily to the worſt, and the <hi>Germans</hi> were forced to retreat, which made him betake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to places of more ſecurity.</p>
               <p>Thus things continued till the year 1663, at which time the <hi>Turks</hi> did not only invade <hi>Tranſyvania</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Turks</hi> ſucceſs in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </note> but ſome of the Emperors Hereditary Countries alſo, &amp; in <hi>July</hi> the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> came into <hi>Hungary</hi> with an Army of above an hundred thouſand men, at leaſt an hundred great Guns, and all other proviſions anſwerable. His firſt work was to lay two Bridges over the <hi>Danow,</hi> one neer <hi>Gran,</hi> and the other neer <hi>Parkham;</hi> ſo that it was doubtful whether he would fall upon <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> or upon <hi>Raab;</hi> but the continual rains, which cauſed the <hi>Danow</hi> to overflow, hindred him for a time; yet at length he paſſed over ſome of his Army at the Bridge neer <hi>Parkham,</hi> whereupon Count <hi>Forgatz,</hi> the Governour of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel,</hi> with ſix thouſand men aſſaulted thoſe that were come over, <hi>July</hi> 28, but the number being greater than he expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and more haſtning over to them, he was compaſſed about with his enemies,<note place="margin">The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts beaten.</note> and though his <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Heyducks</hi> fought ſtoutly, yet being overpowred, moſt of them were cut in pieces, himſelf with ſome few others getting into <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Newhauſel</hi> taken.</note> This the <hi>Vizier</hi> preſently beſieged, and at length it was ſurrended to him upon honourable Conditions: So that <hi>Septemb.</hi> 26. the Chriſtians marched out being two thouſand and almoſt five hundred able men, with Arms and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38150:17"/> four pieces of Ordinance, the enemy finding in the City, ſeventy Peices of Ordinance, and great ſtore of Arms, Powder, Wine, Meal, and Corn.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time ſome <hi>Tartars,</hi> and others, forced away over the River <hi>Wargh,</hi> cutting in pieces ſuch Chriſtians as guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the paſs, and ſo croſſing the Mountains they went into <hi>Moravia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moravia</hi> plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                  </note> where they plundered, and burnt Towns and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages for ten days together, and then they paſſed into <hi>Auſtria,</hi> where alſo they made great ſpoil, and having laden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Booty, they returned to the Camp at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then did the <hi>Vizer,</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> make an attempt upon <hi>Serinſwar,</hi> and another upon <hi>Clauſenburg,</hi> but at both places they were repulſed:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serini</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades the <hi>Turks.</hi>
                  </note> and Count <hi>Serini</hi> in the mean time with an Army of <hi>Croats,</hi> and others, made an incurſion into ſome of the <hi>Turks</hi> countries, where he did them much harm, and at his return was made <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of all the Emperors Forces, then rendevouzed at <hi>Presburg,</hi> under their former General <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecuculi:</hi> Towards which place the <hi>Vizier</hi> now advanced, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out rumors that he ment to Attaque it. But ſuch had been the care of <hi>Serini</hi> in furniſhing of it, himſelf alſo being in it, that the <hi>Vizier,</hi> contenting himſelf with the taking in of ſome other Towns and places of leſſer concernment, he made an Honourable retreat, and preſently beſieged <hi>Niutra,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Niutra</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </note> a very ſtrong City, not far from <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> which after a while, was ſurrendred to him upon Articles: which Victories, and his faithful performance of Covenants, made way for his ſucceſſes elſewhere: For <hi>Tyrnaw,</hi> and ſome other Towns opened their Gates to him, upon his promiſe that they ſhould enjoy their Religion, and Liberties without diſturbance.</p>
               <p>Then did he beſiege <hi>Schinta,</hi> a very ſtrong Fortreſs, but <hi>October</hi> being almoſt gone, and Winter coming on apace, he was forced to raiſe his ſiege, and to provide Winter Quarters for his Army.<note place="margin">The <hi>Viſier</hi> retreats.</note> He left four thouſand men in <hi>Newhauſel</hi> and fifteen hundred in <hi>Niutra,</hi> beſides ten thouſand others to be ready upon all emergencies; and to encreaſe the danger of the Imperialiſts, <hi>Apaffi,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> declared himſelf an enemy to them, having a promiſe from the <hi>Great Turk</hi> of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38150:18"/> Kingdom of <hi>Hungary</hi> to be conferred upon him when it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apaffies</hi> ſucceſſes.</note>
                  <hi>Apaffies</hi> firſt deſign was upon the <hi>Mine-Towns,</hi> whence they have their Gold: but that which hindred his proceeedings was this; there were <hi>Novigrad,</hi> and <hi>Leventz</hi> in his way, two very ſtrong Places and well fortified and Garriſoned. <hi>Leventz</hi> was firſt attaqued by him, and though there was nothing wanting for the ſecuring of the place, yet after a while it was ſurrendred upon Articles, which were punctually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
               <p>From thence he marched to <hi>Nevigrad</hi> in Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> which after a ſtout, but ſhort reſiſtance, was ſurrendred to him: and though ſome Regiments were ſent by the Emperor to ſecure the Mine-Towns, yet <hi>Apaffi</hi> took in <hi>Shomnitz, Crem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitz,</hi> and ſome other of them.</p>
               <p>The Emperor himſelf went from <hi>Vienna</hi> to <hi>Regenſpurgh,</hi> where he had ſummoned a <hi>Diet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Diet at <hi>Ratisbone.</hi>
                  </note> to conſider with the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> how theſe evils might be prevented, leaving to Govern in his abſence, the Archduke <hi>Charles Joſeph</hi> his Brother, who, not long after, fell ſick and died.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serini</hi>'s ſucceſſes.</note>In the mean while <hi>Apaffi</hi> had ſurrendred to him <hi>Zekelkeyt,</hi> and <hi>Clauſenburg,</hi> which ſtrong holds had been held by the Emperor ever ſince the death of <hi>Rakoczi.</hi> The <hi>Tartars</hi> that were quartered in <hi>Hungary,</hi> expecting Froſts wherein they might be enabled to action, the Winter proving open, and mild, the places and Garriſons wherein they were being overburthened, they began to want proviſions, ſo that they were forced to diſperſe themſelves for better accommodation; which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage Count <hi>Serini</hi> taking, by the benefit of a ſudden Froſt, with an Army of about thirty five thouſand, he fell into the enemies Country in the lower <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Croatia,</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing as far as <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> where there was Bridge neer to the conjunction of the <hi>Danow</hi> with the <hi>Dravus,</hi> over which the <hi>Turks</hi> uſed to paſs from <hi>Belgrade,</hi> now <hi>Greek Weiſſenburg,</hi> into the <hi>Lower Hungary;</hi> the Count knowing what diſadvantage the breaking down of this Bridge would be to them in reference to the enſuing <hi>Campagnia,</hi> notwithſtanding all oppoſition made by the enemy, he ſo maimed, and disjoynted it, that part of it fell
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38150:18"/> into the <hi>Dravus:</hi> ſince when they have been very buſie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing it.</p>
               <p>Count <hi>Serini</hi> having ſucceeded ſo well in this enterpriſe, laid all the Country waſt with fire, and ſword, and ſo return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Yet in his way, he came by <hi>Quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Eccleſiae,</hi> and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned it; the Town ſeemed to be willing to Parlie till they had drawn ſome of his forces within the reach of their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and then let fly amongſt them, at which time many of his men, and ſome eminent Officers were ſlain, which ſo incenſed <hi>Serini,</hi> that he took the Town by ſtorm, ſacked, and burnt it,<note place="margin">Quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Eccleſiae <hi>burnt.</hi>
                  </note> the Souldiers and many others retreating into the Caſtle; which <hi>Serini</hi> thought not fit to beſiege, then paſſing by <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth,</hi> he fell upon <hi>Segeſs,</hi> which he took by aſſault, but with the loſs of more of his Officers of note; and ſo by <hi>Canyſia</hi> (which he durſt not adventure upon) his Army being much diminiſhed) he returned home.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Deſcription of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> with a Catalogue of the <hi>Vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vods,</hi> and Princes thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TRanſylvania</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Moldavia:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tranſylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</note> On the Weſt with the Upper <hi>Hungary:</hi> On the North with <hi>Ruſſia Nigra,</hi> a Province of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Poland,</hi> from which it is ſeparated by the <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains: On the South with <hi>Raſcia,</hi> and <hi>Walachia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It took its name from the great Woods lying betwixt it and <hi>Hungary,</hi> the <hi>Latine</hi> Name ſignifying the Countrey beyond the Woods. By the <hi>Dutch</hi> it's called <hi>Seber Burgen,</hi> from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Caſtles, or ſtrong holds, that were anciently built in it, to defend the Frontiers.</p>
               <p>It is environed round about with high Hills and Woods,<note place="margin">It's ſtrong ſituation.</note> as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38150:19"/> with Walls, ſo that the paſſages into it are very difficult; by reaſon alſo of certain Rivers, and Brooks, amongſt which there is the River of <hi>Alutha,</hi> where there is a ſtrong Caſtle built, called <hi>Roteth,</hi> to defend the paſſage: And upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Mariſcus,</hi> there is another Fort, called <hi>Broſch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of it.</note>The ſoil doth naturally abound with Wines, Corn, and Fruit, of which it yielded ſuch plenty in the time of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that the Emperor <hi>Trajan</hi> cauſed a piece of mony to be coined, which had the Figure of <hi>Ceres,</hi> holding in one hand a <hi>Cornu-Copia,</hi> and in the other a plain <hi>Tablet,</hi> with this inſcription, <hi>Abundantia Daciae.</hi> The abundance of <hi>Dacia.</hi> More parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, beſides the great plenty of Wheat, and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Wines, it yields great ſtore of Cherries, Damaſcens, Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotoons, Musk-melons, not inferior to thoſe of <hi>Italy.</hi> As alſo Centaury great ſtore, and many other Medecinal Plants. Some Mines of Gold, and Silver they have, and many more of Iron, Braſs, and Copper; and not a few Veins of Salt, and Sulphur. Of Cattle they have ſuch abundance, that many times large Oxen are ſold for a <hi>Floren,</hi> or half a Crown a piece. They have alſo a notable breed of Horſes, which are exceeding ſwift, whoſe manes hang down to the ground: Not to ſay any thing of that variety of wild Beaſts which they have in their Woods, and Forreſts; and of all ſorts of Fowl, both for food, and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the People.</note>The People are much of the ſame nature with the <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> to whom they have been of a long time ſubject, but ſomewhat more ſtubborn, and untractable; they ſpeak the ſame Language that the <hi>Hungarians</hi> uſe,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonian</hi> language.</note> with ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the <hi>Dialect</hi> onely. They were converted at the ſame time to the Chriſtian Faith, and have the ſame forms of Eccleſiaſtical Government; and the ſame variety of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In former times they uſed to read as the <hi>Jews</hi> do, from the right hand to the left: but of late, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form herein to the Weſtern Nations, from whom they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally deſcended.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Their Original.</note>It's evident that the People of this Country are the Progeny of the <hi>Saxons</hi> by their <hi>Saxon</hi> Language, yet in part retained: For we find that <hi>Charlemayne,</hi> like a Politick Conquerer, tranſplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38150:19"/> many of <hi>Saxons</hi> hither, that thereby he might weaken their ſtrength at home, and by them fortifie the Bounds of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. There is alſo a Story cited by <hi>Verſtigan</hi> to confirm it; Which is this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Halberſtade</hi> was beyond credit, troubled with Rats,<note place="margin">A ſtrange ſtory.</note> which a Muſician, which they called the <hi>Peed Piper,</hi> undertook for a great Maſs of Money to deſtroy, which they agreed to. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he tuned his Pipes, and all the Rats in the Town dancing after him, were drowned in the next River. This done, he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his pay, which they denied him; Whereupon he ſtrikes up a new fit of mirth, and all the children, both Males, and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males in the Town, followed him into the Hill <hi>Hamelen,</hi> which preſently cloſed again. The Parents miſs their children, but could never hear news of them (believe it who pleaſes) till now of late ſome have found them in <hi>Tranſylvania.</hi> This marvellous accident is ſaid to have happened <hi>July</hi> 22. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1376, Since which time, it's ſaid, that the People of <hi>Halberſtade</hi> permit not any Drum, Pipe, or other Inſtrument to be ſounded in that ſtreet: and they eſtabliſhed a Decree that in all writings of Contracts, and Bargains, after the Date of our Lord Chriſts Nativity, the date alſo of this their childrens tranſmigration ſhould be added for the remembrance of it.</p>
               <p>But though the <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>Saxons</hi> make up the main Body of the <hi>Tranſylvanians,</hi> yet, having been conquered by the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> they have received many of their Colonies amongſt them; and in the Northern parts of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> there remain ſtill ſome of the old <hi>Scythians,</hi> whih were plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there by <hi>Attila.</hi> Out of all theſe,<note place="margin">The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it.</note> the Body of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is compoſed ſo ſtrong and populous that they are able to raiſe an Army of ninety thouſand men; and actually they did Arm ſix thouſand Horſe, and twelve thouſand Foot for the Battel of <hi>Kereſture; Anno Chriſti</hi> 1596. being more than all <hi>Hungary</hi> ſent to that ſervice by two thouſand.</p>
               <p>Chief Towns in <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> of the foundation of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> or <hi>Saxons,</hi> are; 1. <hi>Hermanſted,</hi> in <hi>Latine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note> 
                  <hi>Hermanopolis,</hi> ſituate on the River <hi>Cibin,</hi> ſo named from one <hi>Herman,</hi> who was the Founder of it. It's little In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38150:20"/> to <hi>Vienna</hi> for ſtrength or greatneſs. It's well fortified both by Art, and Nature: for it ſtands in a Mooriſh place, ſo that the acceſs unto it is very difficult. 2. <hi>Cronſtad,</hi> called in <hi>Latine Corona,</hi> by ſome <hi>Braſſovia,</hi> by others <hi>Stephanopolis,</hi> which name was given to it by <hi>Stephen</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who repaired, and beautified it. It's ſituate on the borders of <hi>Wallachia,</hi> amongſt fruitful Mountains. It's adorned with a fair <hi>Library,</hi> a kind of Univerſity, and it's the moſt noted <hi>Empory,</hi> or Mart-Town in all this Country, unto which there is great reſort, eſpecially in the time of their publick Fairs, by <hi>Turks, Arabians, Greeks, Armenians, Polanders, Walachians,</hi> and other Nations. 3. <hi>Biſtricium,</hi> called by the <hi>Dutch No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren:</hi> It receives it's name from the River <hi>Biſtrice,</hi> which runs through it; It's ſo pleaſant, and ſo ſweet a Town, that there is no mire or durt to be ſeen in it at any time, or if there be, the People preſently cauſe the River, by ſtoping of it, to ſwell over it's Banks, and ſo to cleanſe the ſtreets. 4. <hi>Medieſus</hi> (called by the <hi>Dutch, Meduiſh</hi>) ſo called, <hi>quaſi Medius Conſeſſus,</hi> becauſe it's ſituate in the midſt of the Country. It's a Town almoſt as neat a <hi>Biſtrice.</hi> 5. <hi>Segoſwaria,</hi> or <hi>Scheſburg,</hi> which ſtands on the declivity of a Hill. 6. <hi>Zabeſus,</hi> or <hi>Laiz,</hi> which was onee the chief Town of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> but now it's much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed. It's ſituate in a very deep Valley, well fenced with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and thoſe waters full of Fiſh. 7. <hi>Clauſenbourg;</hi> called in <hi>Latine, Claudionopolis</hi> from the Emperor <hi>Claudius</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, who re-edified it. At the firſt, it was a Colony of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> onely; But of late times the <hi>Hungarians</hi> coming in as Strangers, were at laſt priviledged as Citizens, and inhabit it together with them. The Town is well ſeated in the midſt of a pleaſant Plain, encompaſſed with a hand ſome wall, and beautified with Elegant buildings. 8. <hi>Alba Julia,</hi> called now <hi>Weiſenberg.</hi> It's ſituate on a ſimall Brook called <hi>Oratas,</hi> whence it had it's Name. It's built on the ſide of a Hill neer the River <hi>Maruch,</hi> or <hi>Murſe:</hi> It overlooks a large fruitful Plain. It was heretofore a Biſhops See, and the ordena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reſidence of the Prince, or <hi>Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Tranſylvania:</hi> but of late it hath been a Garriſon of <hi>Hungarian</hi> Souldiers, who held it for the Emperor, as King of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:38150:20"/>
               <p>The Chief Towns belonging to the <hi>Hungarians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The chief Towns belonging to the <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
                  </note> and by them inhabited, are 1. <hi>Varadin,</hi> much mentioned in the ſtories of theſe later times ſince the Invaſion of the <hi>Turks:</hi> It's ſituate on the Borders of <hi>Hungary.</hi> 2. <hi>Thorda,</hi> built in or neer the place, called by <hi>Ptolmoy, Salinae,</hi> becauſe of the abundance of Salt-pits which were then about it. 3. <hi>Engue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,</hi> by the <hi>Romans</hi> called <hi>Annium,</hi> from a Cauſey leading to it, which was raiſed by one <hi>Annius,</hi> and from him ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; ſome fragments whereof are ſtill remaining. 4. <hi>Deva,</hi> which is remarkable for having a vein of the beſt Wines about it, not inferior to thoſe of <hi>Venuſium</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi> 6. <hi>Zilahi.</hi> 7. <hi>Gela,</hi> of both which, little is memorable. 8. <hi>Millenbach,</hi> not far from which, betwixt it, and the Town of <hi>Braſs,</hi> is a very ſtrong Fortreſs, commanding a ſtreight, and narrow paſſage leading into the Country of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the North part of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Siculi</hi> in part of it.</note> lyeth the Province called <hi>Zacultia,</hi> inhabited by the <hi>Siculi,</hi> or the old brood of <hi>Scythians,</hi> brought hither by <hi>Attila,</hi> when he firſt conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Country. They are a People which have much in them of the ancient <hi>Hunn,</hi> and heretofore had a Language peculiar to themſelves; But now they ſpeak the <hi>Hungarian</hi> generally, differing onely in the <hi>Dialect.</hi> But though, by the neceſſity of Commerce, and co-habitation, they have learned the ſame Language, yet they ſtill retain their ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and are Governed by their own Laws. They are a Warlike People, and live after the ſame manner as the <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> do, being divided into ſeven <hi>Cantons,</hi> each <hi>Canton</hi> being abſolute in and of it ſelf; but all united with the <hi>Tranſylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and amongſt themſelves, for the defence of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try againſt the pretention of the <hi>German,</hi> and <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors; and though they acknowledge ſome ſubjection to the Emperor, as King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> yet it is but what they liſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, being anciently priviledged from all Taxes, more than the paying of a Bull for every Houſhold at the Coronation of a new King; when, and how often ſo ever it falls out. In former times, no Nobility, nor any one of better means, and greater eminence than other, was known amongſt them,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38150:21"/> but of later times ſome have overtopped others, both in power, and title, as in other places.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">They im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Goſpel.</note>
                  <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> was Conquered by <hi>Stephen,</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Saint,</hi> by whoſe perſwaſion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements, they received the Goſpel, after which time, as a member of that Kingdom, in was Governed by Deputies, whom they called <hi>Vayvods</hi> of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> (the word <hi>Vayvod</hi> ſignifying as much as <hi>Praefectus Militiae,</hi> or a Lord Lieutenant) a name, by reaſon of the greatneſs of his place and power, of moſt authority in that Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Vayvods,</hi> and Princes of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> ſince the time of <hi>John Huniades.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1400. <hi>John,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Huniades,</hi> was made <hi>Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> the fourth. He was a Valiant, and Renowned Champion, and a great defender of his Country againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> whom he overthrew in many Battels, eſpecially in that of <hi>Maxons,</hi> where he ſlew of them fifty thouſand. He dyed about the year 1458.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Steven,</hi> of the Noble Family of the <hi>Battori;</hi> He was <hi>Vayvod</hi> in the time of <hi>Matthias,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Corvinus,</hi> Son of <hi>Huniades,</hi> and King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> about the year 1470.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> the ſecond, ſurnamed <hi>de Sepuſio</hi> was <hi>Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania,</hi> about the year 1527, and was afterwards choſen King of <hi>Hungary</hi> upon the Death of <hi>Lewis</hi> the ſecond; and was thence ejected by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and reſtored to his Kingdom again by <hi>Solyman</hi> the great <hi>Turk.</hi> He died <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1540.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Americus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Veradium,</hi> was made <hi>Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania</hi> by <hi>John de Sepuſio,</hi> when he took the Crown of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi> He was treacherouſly murthered for not complying with the <hi>Turks. Anno Chriſt</hi> 1534.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen Mayſat,</hi> a Noble, <hi>Hungarian</hi> but extreamly ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; Not long after the Death of <hi>Americus,</hi> he uſurped the <hi>Vayvodſhip,</hi> and was confirmed therein, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1540.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the third, the Son of <hi>John de Sepuſio,</hi> was made <hi>Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> whilſt he was an Infant by <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1541.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:38150:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the fourth, ſurnamed <hi>Battori,</hi> was made <hi>Vayvod</hi> by the great <hi>Turk;</hi> and afterwards, upon the commendation of <hi>Amurath</hi> the third, was choſen King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christopher Battori,</hi> Brother to <hi>Stephen,</hi> ſucceeded him in the <hi>Vayvodſhip,</hi> when his Brother <hi>Stephen</hi> was choſen King of <hi>Poland.</hi> He was the firſt that, leaving the Title of <hi>Vayvod,</hi> called himſelf Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania.</hi> 1575.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> Son of <hi>Chriſtopher Battori,</hi> was the next. He was a gallant Prince, who ſhook off the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> yoke, defeated ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Armies, and ſlew ſome of their <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s. But not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to hold out againſt ſo Potent an Enemy, he reſigned his intereſt in <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> to the Emperor <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> having for it in Exchange, the Dukedoms of <hi>Oppelen,</hi> and <hi>Ratibor</hi> in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and an annual Penſion of fifty thouſand <hi>Joakims.</hi> But finding his Penſion ill paid, he reaſſumed his Princedom and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned it again to a Kinſman.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andrew Battori,</hi> Couſin to <hi>Sigiſmund;</hi> He was ſlain within the year by the <hi>Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Walachia. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1599.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> was admitted Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania. Anno Christi</hi> 1601. upon the ſecond Reſignation of <hi>Sigiſmund:</hi> But his Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>having themſelves very inſolently, <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> was called back again, but never was well ſetled.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin Battori,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Botſcay,</hi> ſucceeded in the Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> upon the Death of <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> by the power of the <hi>Turks,</hi> by whoſe help he cleared the Country of the <hi>German</hi> Souldiers, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1604.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gabriel Battori,</hi> of the family of the former Princes, ſucceeded in that Principality by the favour of <hi>Achmet,</hi> the <hi>Great Turk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigiſmund Ragotzi,</hi> upon the death of <hi>Gabriel Battori,</hi> was made Prince by the power, and favor of the <hi>Turks. An. Chriſti</hi> 1610.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bethlem Gabor,</hi> by the <hi>Great Turk</hi> was made Prince of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania;</hi> He was a profeſſed enemy to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and maintained great Wars againſt it. <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1620.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Ragotſy,</hi> or <hi>Rakoczi,</hi> ſucceeded his Father in the Principality of <hi>Tranſylvania. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1648. He died <hi>June</hi> the ſixth <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1660.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Rakoczi</hi> the younger, ſucceeded him, who died the laſt Winter. 1663.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:38150:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Radus</hi> was by the <hi>Great Turk</hi> made Prince of <hi>Tranſylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> in the life time of Prince <hi>Rakoczi,</hi> upon ſome diſtaſte that he took againſt him for aſſiſting the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> in his expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into <hi>Poland.</hi> But when <hi>Rakoczi</hi> was dead, the <hi>Turk</hi> laid aſides <hi>Radus,</hi> as unfit for his turn; whereupon one <hi>Barkay,</hi> a Creature of the <hi>Turks,</hi> made himſelf Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania;</hi> whom the <hi>Turk</hi> Protected, and ſupplied with forces againſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Janos,</hi> the right ſucceſſor of <hi>Rakoczi,</hi> whom many of the <hi>Tranſylvanians</hi> received for their Prince; This <hi>Janos</hi> fought <hi>Barkay,</hi> and made a great ſlaughter of his men; But at laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppreſſed with the number of his enemies, he left <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania,</hi> and retreated to <hi>Tockay. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1661.</p>
               <p>Not long after, <hi>Barkay</hi> falling into diſgrace with the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> he put him down, and preferred to his place one <hi>Apaſſi,</hi> who is now living. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1664.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A brief Deſcription of thoſe Neighboring Countries which bound upon, or are neer unto <hi>Hungary,</hi> and are contained in this Map.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sclavonia</hi> Deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sclavonia</hi> deſcribed.</note>
                     <hi>SClavonia</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Servia, Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> and <hi>Epirus:</hi> On the Weſt with <hi>Carniola:</hi> On the North with <hi>Hungary:</hi> On the South with the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea. It's ſo called from the <hi>Sclavy,</hi> a People of <hi>Dalmatia.</hi> It contains in length, from <hi>Arfia</hi> to the River <hi>Drinus,</hi> about eight hundred <hi>Italian</hi> Miles, and in breadth about three hundred twenty five of the ſame miles; the longeſt day is about fifteen hours and an half in Summer.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:38150:22"/>
                  <p>The Country abounds with moſt of thoſe commodities that are found in <hi>Italy,</hi> to which it is little inferior.<note place="margin">The Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of it.</note> It yields Wine and Oyl in great plenty; and hath good ſtore of Cattel, and ſome wild Beaſts: It hath alſo ſome rich veins of Gold and Silver. The Northern parts are Mountainous &amp; cold, not yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wine, or ſuch fruits as require heat; yet they yield good Paſturage, and breed a race of Sheep that have young twice a year, and are ſhorn four times. The Sea coaſt yields ſtore of Fiſh, and very good Havens.</p>
                  <p>The People are couragious, proud, ſtubborn,<note place="margin">The qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of the People</note> and untracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, of ſtrong bodies and conſtitutions, able to endure much drudgery, wherein they are imployed by the <hi>Venetians.</hi> The Chriſtian Faith was firſt planted here, about the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Bald,</hi> Emperor of the Weſt. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 877.<note place="margin">Then Religion.</note> 
                     <hi>Suero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilus</hi> being the firſt of their Kings that embraced the Goſpel. In the Eaſtern parts towards <hi>Greece</hi> they embrace the Religion of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church; and in the Weſtern towards <hi>Italy,</hi> that of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; The <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Religion in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are ſubjected to the <hi>Turks.</hi> The <hi>Sclavonian</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is common to them all.</p>
                  <p>The Chief Mountains in this Country are called <hi>Scardonici;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The mountains and rivers</note> the Chief Rivers are; 1. <hi>Varieca,</hi> which parts it from <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia;</hi> 2. <hi>Arſa,</hi> that bounds it on the Weſt; And 3. <hi>Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> that bounds it on the Eaſt. 4. <hi>Narento,</hi> not far from <hi>Epidaurus.</hi> This Country was anciently called <hi>Illyria,</hi> or <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyricum;</hi> and is ſubdivided into <hi>Windiſmark, Croatia, Boſnia, Dalmatia,</hi> and <hi>Contado Di Zara.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Windiſmark</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Windiſmark</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with part of the Lower <hi>Hungary;</hi> On the Weſt with <hi>Carniola,</hi> or <hi>Krain:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Windiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note> On the North with the River <hi>Dravus;</hi> and on the South with <hi>Croa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi> The Chiefeſt Towns in it are; 1. <hi>Windiſch greits,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note> ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the <hi>Dravus.</hi> 2. <hi>Sagona,</hi> neer unto the <hi>Savus.</hi> 3. <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcha</hi> on the South: And 4. <hi>Zagabria,</hi> on the alſo South of the ſame River. 5. <hi>Novigrod,</hi> on the <hi>Savus,</hi> neer to <hi>Germany.</hi> 6. <hi>Petrowya</hi> at the foot of the Mountaines which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Savus</hi> and the <hi>Dravus,</hi> and divide <hi>Hungary</hi> from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38150:23"/> 
                     <hi>Sclavonia.</hi> 7. <hi>Siſſag,</hi> or <hi>Siſhaken,</hi> ſituate on the <hi>Savus,</hi> over againſt <hi>Zagabria,</hi> where it receiveth the River <hi>Zulph,</hi> famous for the defeat here given to the <hi>Turks, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1593. who hoped by the Conqueſt hereof, to open a free paſſage for themſelves into <hi>Germany;</hi> for which end they ſat down before it with a great Army; but the Town held it out gallantly till it was relieved by the <hi>Germans,</hi> who ſlew of the <hi>Turks</hi> eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in the place, and moſt of the reſt were drowned in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus,</hi> as they fled haſtily from the Conquering Sword.</p>
                  <p>This Province is much of it under the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> as Kings of <hi>Hungary,</hi> to which Crown it belongs, but the North, and Eaſt parts of it, now groan under the yoke of the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Croatia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Croatia</hi> deſcribed.</note>
                     <hi>Croatia</hi> is bounded on the North with <hi>Windiſmark,</hi> from which its parted by the River <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na,</hi> or <hi>Wana;</hi> On the Eaſt with <hi>Boſnia;</hi> On the South with <hi>Liburnia,</hi> or <hi>Contado di Zara:</hi> On the Weſt with <hi>Carniola;</hi> the Country for the moſt part is cold, and mountainous, yet reſonably fruitful, having neceſſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for the life of man, and would yield far more profit to the Inhabitants were it not for the ill neighbourhood of the <hi>Turk,</hi> to whoſe Tyranny, and oppreſſions it is enthralled; the People are good Souldiers, and are called <hi>Crabats.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note>The Chief Towns in it are; 1. <hi>Maſch,</hi> or <hi>Moſth,</hi> border<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon <hi>Germany.</hi> 2. <hi>Oſtrowits,</hi> a ſtrong Fort on the ſame Frontire. 3. <hi>Wihits,</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> called <hi>Bigihen,</hi> the Chief Town of the Country, ſtanding like an Iſland in the River <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na,</hi> and ſtrongly fortified by Art; yet was it taken by the <hi>Turks. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1591. 4 <hi>Zeng.</hi> 5. <hi>Wackat.</hi> 6. <hi>Tarnow.</hi> 7. <hi>Modriſch.</hi> Part of this Country is held by the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the other Part by the <hi>Turks.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Boſnia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Boſnia</hi> deſcribed.</note>
                     <hi>Boſnia</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Servia;</hi> On the Weſt with <hi>Croatia;</hi> On the North with the River <hi>Savus;</hi> On the Eaſt with the Lower <hi>Hungary;</hi> and on the South with <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note> The chiefeſt Towns in it are; 1. <hi>Jaitza</hi> or <hi>Jaziga,</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate on the top of an high Hill, the bottom whereof is almoſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38150:23"/> compaſſed with two Rivers, which there uniting, paſs into the <hi>Savus.</hi> The Town, by reaſon of the ſteepneſs of the Hill, the unfoardableneſs of the River, and the inacceſſible Caſtle, is counted impregnable; 2. <hi>Warbaſoni,</hi> the Chief Town of the Country, but unwalled. 3. <hi>Cazach.</hi> 4. <hi>Schwanica.</hi> 5. <hi>Dorobiza,</hi> the firſt Town taken by <hi>Mahomet</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> in his Conqueſt of this Kingdom. 6. <hi>Clyſſa;</hi> This Country did formerly belong to the Crown of <hi>Hungary;</hi> till it was ſurprized by the <hi>Turks, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1464.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Dalmatia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dalmatia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dalmatia</hi> deſcribed.</note> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Albania,</hi> from which it's parted by the River <hi>Driſo;</hi> On the Eaſt with <hi>Variecha,</hi> which divides it from <hi>Liburnia:</hi> On the North with <hi>Boſnia,</hi> and on the South with the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea.</p>
                  <p>Places of moſt note in it are: 1. <hi>Sebenic,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note> on the Sea ſhoar. 2. <hi>Salona.</hi> 3. <hi>Spalato,</hi> a Sea Town, and an Archbiſhops See; Of this See was <hi>Marcus Antonius de Dominis,</hi> who ſeeming to lothe the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Superſtition, fled into <hi>England, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1618, where he found favourable intertainment; and having here, both by Preaching, and writing, laboured to overthrow the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1622, he declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be of another mind, and returning again to <hi>Rome,</hi> he wrote very reproachfully of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> yet it ſeems, they durſt not truſt him, but impriſoned him in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Angelo,</hi> where he died, and his dead body they burnt to aſhes. 4. <hi>Almiſſa,</hi> ſituated on a high Rock, and defended with an impregnable Caſtle. 5. <hi>Stagno,</hi> which ſtands upon the Point of a long and ſpacious <hi>Cherſoneſe,</hi> not far from which, the River <hi>Narento</hi> falls into the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea. 6. <hi>Caſtle Novo,</hi> a ſtrong Fortreſs within the Gulph <hi>Catharo,</hi> now in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Turks.</hi> 7. <hi>Antibari,</hi> on the Eaſtern ſide of the Bay, an Archbiſhop See, but now in the hands of the <hi>Turks.</hi> 8. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharo,</hi> on the ſame ſide of the Bay; A ſtrong hold of the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> againſt the <hi>Turks;</hi> It gives denomination to the Bay, now called <hi>Golpho de Catharo.</hi> 9. <hi>Deleigno.</hi> 10. <hi>Scutari,</hi> more within Land, founded on a ſteep Rock; It reſiſted for a year, the whole power of <hi>Mahomet</hi> the ſecond, that battered it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38150:24"/> with ſeventy pieces of Ordinance, whereof ſome of them carried a Bullet of twelve hundred weight, and at laſt was taken by the <hi>Turks, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1578. Not far from this Town is the great Lake of <hi>Scutari,</hi> an hundred &amp; thirty miles in compaſs, environed on all ſides with Mountains; but only on the North, out of which Iſſueth the River <hi>Driana,</hi> which part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sclavonia</hi> from <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and <hi>Servia,</hi> runneth into the <hi>Savus.</hi> 11. <hi>Aleſio,</hi> the furtheſt Town of all <hi>Dalmatia</hi> towards <hi>Greece;</hi> where the famous <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> was buried. 12. <hi>Medon,</hi> where the Emperor <hi>Diocleſian</hi> was born. 13. <hi>Dalminium,</hi> once the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of this Country, ſituate on the River <hi>Drinus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Betwixt the <hi>Cherſoneſe</hi> of <hi>Staguo,</hi> and the Gulph of <hi>Catharo</hi> ſtands the Town, and Territory of <hi>Raguſi,</hi> Coverned by their own Laws, and Magiſtrates, as a free Commonwealth, paying only to the <hi>Turk</hi> fourteen thouſand <hi>Zechines</hi> yearly for a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, and as much in Preſents, for which they are diſcharged of all cuſtoms, and impoſitions within his Dominions; It hath a commodious Port; the Town is well built, fortified with Walls, and a ſtrong Caſtle. It's an Archbiſhop See, and is made rich by Marchandiſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Dacia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dacia</hi> deſcribed.</note>
                     <hi>Dacia</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea, and ſome part of <hi>Thrace;</hi> On the Weſt with <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Sclavonia;</hi> on the North with <hi>Podolia,</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>Poland;</hi> and on the South with the reſt of <hi>Thracia,</hi> and <hi>Macedonia:</hi> it lies on both ſides of the <hi>Danow,</hi> frontiring all along upon the Upper, and Lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> and part of <hi>Sclavonia:</hi> It contains in it theſe Provinces; 1. <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> before deſcribed. 2. <hi>Moldovia.</hi> 3. <hi>Walachia.</hi> 4. <hi>Raſcia.</hi> 5. <hi>Servia.</hi> 6. <hi>Bulgaria;</hi> the firſt four are on the North ſide of the <hi>Danow;</hi> the two laſt on the South thereof. Of theſe in order,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Moldovia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Moldovia</hi> deſcribed. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities.</note>
                     <hi>Moldavia</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with the Sea; on the Weſt with <hi>Tranſylvania;</hi> On the North with the River <hi>Nieſter;</hi> and on the South with <hi>Walachia.</hi> It's fruitfull in Corn, Wine, Graſs, and Wood; It's moſt uſed for Paſturage, wanting Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38150:24"/> to till it: It breeds ſtore of Beef and Mutton, whereof it ſend much abroad into other Countries. The Port Towns are full of <hi>Armenians, Jews, Hungarians,</hi> and <hi>Raguſian</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, the Country is almoſt round, the <hi>Diamiter</hi> neer three hundred <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles. Its under the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Walachia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Walachia</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Walachia</hi> deſcribed.</note> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Moldovia,</hi> and a branch of <hi>Ister;</hi> On the Weſt with <hi>Raſcia;</hi> On the North with <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>Moldavia;</hi> and on the South wholly with the <hi>Danow</hi> that parts it from <hi>Servia,</hi> and <hi>Bulgary.</hi> It's in length five hundred miles, and in breadth an hundred and twenty. For the moſt part it's plain,<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</note> and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, abounding with Cattle and an excellent breed of Horſes; Hath ſome Mines of Gold, Silver, and Iron; Saltpits, and all things neceſſary for the life of man; They receive their <hi>Vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vods</hi> from the <hi>Great Turk.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other Provinces before-mentioned, not touching upon <hi>Hungary,</hi> nor contained in this Map, I ſhall ſay nothing of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Auſtria</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Austria</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auſtria</hi> deſcribed.</note> hath on the Eaſt, <hi>Hungary,</hi> from which it's parted by the River <hi>Rab;</hi> On the Weſt <hi>Bavaria;</hi> On the North <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia;</hi> On the Weſt <hi>Teya,</hi> that ſeparates it from <hi>Moravia,</hi> and on the South <hi>Styria,</hi> or <hi>Steirmark;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</note> The air is generally healthful, and the earth fruitful, yielding a plentiful increaſe without ſoiling, and ſo eaſie of tillage, that on the North ſide of the <hi>Danow,</hi> they plow with one Horſe. It's plentiful of Grain and Wine; yields great ſtore of excellent Safforn, and ſome ſalt. It's divided by the River <hi>Danow</hi> into the Upper, and Lower <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Chief Towns in the Upper <hi>Auſtria</hi> are; 1. <hi>Gmund,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note> ſeated on a Lake called <hi>Gemunder</hi> See, bordering on <hi>Bavaria.</hi> 2. <hi>Lints,</hi> ſeated on the confluence of the River <hi>Draun</hi> with the <hi>Danow.</hi> 3. <hi>Walkenſtein</hi> on the <hi>Ens,</hi> neer <hi>Steirmark.</hi> 4. <hi>Ens,</hi> on the fall of that River into the <hi>Danow.</hi> 5. <hi>Waldhoven,</hi> neer the head of the River <hi>Ips.</hi> 6. <hi>Ips,</hi> ſeated on the River ſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38150:25"/> 7. <hi>Newful,</hi> on a great Lake ſo named. 8. <hi>Wels,</hi> on the <hi>Danow.</hi> 9. <hi>Haimburg,</hi> on the confluence of the <hi>Danow</hi> and the River <hi>Mark,</hi> where grows ſome Ginger. 10. <hi>Newſtat,</hi> built of late. 11. <hi>Vienna,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vienna</hi> deſcribed.</note> ſeated on the Bank of the <hi>Danow,</hi> well ſtored wich private and Publick Buildings, each houſe having great ſtore of Cellaredge; The ſtreets are generally ſpacious, and well paved, clean and ſweet even in Winter. It's fenced with a mighty wall, and very deep ditches on all parts, and many Bulwarks, Towers, and Ramparts; Eſteemed the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hold in Chriſtendom againſt the <hi>Turks. Anno Chriſti</hi> 1526, it gave a famous repulſe to them, at what time <hi>Solyman</hi> the <hi>Magnificent</hi> beſieged it with two hundred thouſand men; But by the valour of <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond, Prince Elector Palatine, and other Princes, he was compelled to retire with the loſs of eighty thouſand men. It's the uſual reſidence of the <hi>German</hi> Emperors; It was made a Univerſity <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1356. It's adorned with an Epiſcopal See, many Magnificent Churches, and ſtately Monaſteries; with a ſumptuous, and Princely Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. In the Lower <hi>Auſtria</hi> there are few Towns of any note.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Stiermark</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stiermark</hi> deſcribed.</note>
                     <hi>Stiria,</hi> or <hi>Stiermark</hi> is bounded on the North with <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria;</hi> on the South with <hi>Carinthia;</hi> On the Eaſt with <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary;</hi> and on the Weſt with <hi>Carniola.</hi> It extends in length an hundred and ten miles, and in breadth not above ſixty. The whole Country is Mountainous and Hilly by reaſon of the branches of their neighbouring <hi>Alps,</hi> and rich only in Minerals.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note>The Chief Towns in it, are: 1. <hi>Grats,</hi> ſeated upon the River <hi>Mur.</hi> A Town once full of Proteſtants, who could not be forced from the free exerciſe of Religion, till the year 1598, in which <hi>Margaret,</hi> Siſter to <hi>Ferdinand de Gratz,</hi> was by the Citizens Nobly intertained, with whom entred ſo many Souldiers, as overpowred the City, and fourteen Proteſtant Miniſters were preſently baniſhed. 2. <hi>Rachelſpurg.</hi> 3. <hi>Pruck,</hi> both ſituate on the <hi>Mur.</hi> 4. <hi>Stechaw,</hi> an Epiſcopal See, ſeated on the <hi>Dravus.</hi> 5. <hi>Petaw,</hi> ſtanding ſomewhat higher on the <hi>Dravus,</hi> 6. <hi>Lamboch,</hi> on the <hi>Dravus</hi> alſo. 7. <hi>Veiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperg,</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:38150:25"/> on the River <hi>Kainach.</hi> 8. <hi>Cely.</hi> 9. <hi>Cainiſia,</hi> a well fortified Town, and the ſtrongeſt Bulwork in this Country againſt the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Carinthia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Carinthia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Carinthia</hi> deſcribed.</note> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> called <hi>Karnten,</hi> which is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Stiermark,</hi> and the River <hi>Levandt:</hi> On the Weſt with the <hi>Diſtrict</hi> of <hi>Saltzburg,</hi> and the River <hi>Saltzach;</hi> On the North with <hi>Auſtria;</hi> and on the South with <hi>Carniola,</hi> and the River <hi>Dravus,</hi> It's ſituate in the worſt part of the <hi>Alps,</hi> and is poor and barren, except only in Minerals; extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all along the <hi>Dravus</hi> for a hundred Engliſh miles in length, and forty ſeven in breadth, betwixt that River, and the <hi>Mur,</hi> by which it is bounded.</p>
                  <p>The chief Towns<note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note> in it are. 1. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Veit,</hi> ſituate at the meeting of the <hi>Glan,</hi> and the <hi>Winies,</hi> adorned with a ſpacious market-place, and a beautiful Conduit. 2. <hi>Vittach,</hi> ſeated on the <hi>Dravus</hi> in a fruitful Valley, encompaſſed about with Rocks; the Houſes are adorned on the outſide with painted Sories, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry delightful to behold. 3. <hi>Gurch,</hi> a ſmall Town, but an Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal See. 4. <hi>Clangfoot,</hi> on the Lake called <hi>Werd-Zee,</hi> a well ſenced place. 5. <hi>Wolſperg,</hi> on the <hi>Lavandt,</hi> neer to <hi>Steir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi> 6. <hi>Lavamundt,</hi> an Epiſcopal See on the ſame border, ſituate where that River falls into the <hi>Dravus.</hi> 7. <hi>Freiſach,</hi> a very ancient Town, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Bavaria</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bavaria,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bavaria</hi> deſcribed.</note> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Auſtria;</hi> On the Weſt with the River <hi>Lech,</hi> which parts it from <hi>Schawben;</hi> On the North with the Upper <hi>Palatinate;</hi> and on the South with <hi>Tirol,</hi> and <hi>Carinthia.</hi> It's divided into three Parts. 1. The <hi>Higher,</hi> lying towards the <hi>Alps</hi> of <hi>Tirol.</hi> 2. The <hi>Lower,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending all along the Bank of the <hi>Danow.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</note> The <hi>Diſtrict</hi> of <hi>Saltzburg,</hi> ſituate betwixt the <hi>Inn,</hi> and <hi>Auſtria:</hi> all three being much overſpread with Woods and Forreſts, the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the once famous <hi>Hercinian Forreſt;</hi> The <hi>Higher</hi> lying towards the <hi>Alps,</hi> is cold and barren; the <hi>Lower</hi> is more fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and better planted. All have great ſtore of Timber for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38150:26"/> building, and of fuell for the fire; and multitudes of Swine are ſed with Maſt in the Woods.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note>The principal Cities in the <hi>Higher Bavaria,</hi> are, 1. <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen,</hi> the Dukes ſeat, ſtanding on the River <hi>Iſer,</hi> in a very ſweet, and pleaſant foil, amongſt Ponds and Groves, daintily interlaced with pretty Rivulets, and enriched with fruitful Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens; that of the Dukes being hardly to be Paralleld: It's a large and Populous City, adorned with many ſpecious Publick Buildings, as Churches, Turrets, Libraries, the Senate Houſe, or Guild-Hall, and Market-place of rare and excellent Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. Amongſt which is a Library in the Dukes Pallace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are about eleven thouſand Volumes, moſt of them Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts. This City was made by <hi>Maximilian</hi> the late Duke, the receptacle for all the ſpoils which he got in his <hi>German</hi> Wars: So that when the Town was taken by <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> he found in it an hundred and forty Braſs pieces of Ordnance, in one of which, he had thirty thouſand Crowns of Gold. 2. <hi>Landsberg,</hi> upon the <hi>Leck,</hi> neer the <hi>Alps</hi> of <hi>Tirol;</hi> once a ſtrong City, but diſmantled by the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi> 3. <hi>Mertenwald,</hi> a beautiful Town, ſeated neer the <hi>Alps.</hi> 4. <hi>Fridberg,</hi> a well fortified Town.</p>
                  <p>In the Lower <hi>Bavaria</hi> theſe places are of moſt note; 1. <hi>Rain,</hi> ſeated on the <hi>Leck,</hi> neer to the place where it falls into the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now;</hi> Memorable for the fight between the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Bavarians,</hi> when the ſaid King paſſed his forces over that River, in which <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Tilly</hi> received that wound where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he died ſhortly after at <hi>Ingolstad.</hi> 2. <hi>Newburg</hi> upon the <hi>Danow,</hi> not far from the <hi>Rain;</hi> the firſt Town in <hi>Bavaria,</hi> taken in by the <hi>Swedes</hi> after the former fight. 3. <hi>Ingolſtad,</hi> made a Univerſity, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1410 A place ſo ſtrongly fortified both by Art and Nature, that it ſeems impregnable: Here the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> found a check to his proceedings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forced to raiſe his Siege, and follow other enterpriſes. 4. <hi>Regensberg,</hi> or <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> on the <hi>Danow</hi> alſo, where the late <hi>Diet</hi> was held; It's a fair, rich, and populous City, beautified with Multitudes of Churches, and Monaſteries, made of late the ordinary place for the General <hi>Diets</hi> of the Empire. It's an Imperial City, but was unexpectedly ſieized on by the Duke
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38150:26"/> of <hi>Bavaria</hi> when the <hi>Swedes</hi> firſt got footing in his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and was held by him with a very ſtrong Garriſon after the loſs of <hi>Munchen,</hi> till at laſt it was won from him by the <hi>Swedes, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1633. 5. <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> ſeated on the <hi>Danow</hi> where it meets with the <hi>Inn,</hi> and the <hi>Ils,</hi> by which it's divided into three Towns, <hi>Paſſaw, Innſtade,</hi> and <hi>Illſtade.</hi> A rich City, and Epiſcopal See. A place famous for the many meetings of the <hi>German</hi> Princes, eſpecially for that, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1552, wherein it was agreed, that, all quarrels laid aſide, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants ſhould enjoy the free exerciſe of their Religion. 6. <hi>Friſnig,</hi> ſituate on the riſing of a fine round Hill, neer the River <hi>Ambra.</hi> An Epiſcopal See; One of the Biſhops was <hi>Otho Frigenſis,</hi> a good Hiſtorian. 7. <hi>Landſhut,</hi> upon the River <hi>Iſar</hi> in the richeſt, and moſt pleaſant part of all <hi>Bavaria;</hi> A beautiful City, adorned with a Church of moſt curious building, and a magnificent Pallace for the uſe of the Duke. 8. <hi>Freiſtet,</hi> the only Imperial Town, except <hi>Regenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> in all this Dukedom.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Saltzburg</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>The Biſhoprick, or <hi>Diſtrict</hi> of <hi>Saltzburg</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Saltzburg</hi> deſcribed.</note> extends from the <hi>Inn</hi> towards the confines of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> It's a Rocky, dry, and barren Country, excepting only a few Valleys, being ſeated in the midſt of the <hi>Julian Alps.</hi> The principal Town is <hi>Saltz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> ſeated in the River <hi>Saltzach;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note> It's a City ſtrongly ſituate amongſt thoſe Mountains, and beautiful; and an Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops See; when <hi>Luther</hi> firſt endeavoured a Reformation, the Biſhop hereof <hi>(Mattheus Langius)</hi> confeſſed that the Maſs had it's faults, and the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> was much corrupted, and the vitious Lives of Prieſts and Friers fit to be reformed, <hi>Sed quod Miſellus Monachus omnia reformet, id non eſſe tolerabile:</hi> But that ſuch a ſorry fellow as <hi>Luther</hi> ſhould attempt the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that, by no means was to be endured. 2. <hi>Newkirch,</hi> on the ſame River, and neer the Head thereof. 3. <hi>Rotenburg,</hi> on the Eaſt ſide of the <hi>Inn,</hi> bordering on <hi>Bavaria.</hi> 4. <hi>Traun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaim,</hi> upon the River <hi>Traun.</hi> 5. <hi>Wildeſmet,</hi> one of the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt Northward; and 6. <hi>Biſhops-ſtaffe,</hi> one of the moſt Southern Towns in all this Tract.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:38150:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maximilian,</hi> the late Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> out of his zeal to Popery, ſided with <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> in his Wars, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1620, and was General of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt <hi>Frederick,</hi> Count Elector Palatine, choſen King of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> In which, having done great ſervice to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial, and <hi>Roman</hi> intereſt, he was by the ſaid <hi>Ferdinand</hi> inveſted in the Upper <hi>Palatinate,</hi> together with the Electoral dignity, which at firſt was conferred upon him but for his life: yet did the Electors of <hi>Menz, Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburg</hi> then Proteſt againſt it. But afterwards in a Diet at <hi>Prague, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1628, the Electorſhip was ſetled upon him and his Heirs for ever, wherein he was alſo confirmed in the Treaty of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and the Palatine was made an eighth Elector.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Kingdom of <hi>Bohemia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bohemia</hi> dſcribed.</note>
                     <hi>Bohemia</hi> is compaſſed about with Woody Mountains, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times part of the <hi>Hircinian</hi> Forreſt: It's bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Moravia;</hi> On the Weſt with the Upper <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and <hi>Voitland:</hi> On the North with <hi>Miſnia, Luſatia,</hi> and ſome part of <hi>Sileſia:</hi> On the South with Parts of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and <hi>Auſtria.</hi> It contains in compaſs about five hundred and fifty Engliſh Miles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</note>The Soil is indifferently fruitfull, and enriched with Mines of all ſorts, but Gold; Tin they have in good plenty, which was firſt found out there, by a Corniſh man, baniſhed out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Anno Chriſti</hi> 1240. They have great ſtore of Wood, and in ſome of their Forreſts, a Beaſt called a <hi>Lomie,</hi> which hath a Bladder under it's neck full of ſcalding water, with which, when he is hunted, he ſo torments the Dogs, that he eaſily eſcapes them; of Corn they have ſufficient, but no Wine, the air being ſharp and piercing; It yields ſtore of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellent Safforn.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Rivers.</note>The principal Rivers are; 1. The <hi>Elb,</hi> or <hi>Albis,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it's Spring here. 2. <hi>Egra.</hi> 3. The <hi>Muldaw;</hi> and 4. The <hi>Warts,</hi> which three laſt, empty themſelves into the <hi>Elb,</hi> which runs through the midſt of the Country.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The beſt Captain.</note>The famouſeſt Captain was <hi>Ziſca,</hi> who in eleven Battails fought againſt the Pope and his Confederates in the defence of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38150:27"/> the <hi>Huſſites;</hi> In all which, he prevailed, and went away vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious; Inſomuch as at his Death, he willed the <hi>Bohemians</hi> to flea him, and make a Drum of his skin, the ſound whereof, would drive away their enemies.</p>
                  <p>The beſt Schollars they had,<note place="margin">The beſt Schollars.</note> were <hi>John Huſs,</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague;</hi> both burnt at the Council of <hi>Conſtance; Anno Chriſti</hi> 1414. They learned their Doctrine from the Books of <hi>Wickliff,</hi> brought thither by a young Schollar who had been a Student in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Towns of moſt note in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> are, 1. <hi>Budweis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note> towards <hi>Auſtria.</hi> 2. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> neer the head of the <hi>Elb.</hi> 3. <hi>Tabor,</hi> a ſtrong Town built by <hi>Ziſca</hi> to be a place of retreat for his <hi>Huſſites,</hi> thence called <hi>Taborites.</hi> 4. <hi>Jaromir.</hi> 5. <hi>Molmuck,</hi> both upon the <hi>Elb.</hi> 6. <hi>Littomiſſel,</hi> a Biſhops See, bordering upon <hi>Moravia.</hi> 7. <hi>Pilſen,</hi> the laſt Town taken by the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts in the War about the Crown, betrayed to <hi>Tilly</hi> for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by ſome of Count <hi>Manfields</hi> Souldiers in his abſence. 8. <hi>Elbogen,</hi> ſituated on the River <hi>Egra,</hi> much eſteemed for it's Baths. 9. <hi>Egra,</hi> upon the ſame River; A ſtrong Town upon the borders of the Upper <hi>Palatinate:</hi> It;s a large City of three miles Compaſs; having a ſweet air, elegant buildings, a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſite, and a rich Soil: Superior in theſe things to <hi>Prague</hi> it ſelf; 10. <hi>Prague,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prague</hi> deſcribed.</note> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the Kingdom, ſeated in the middeſt thereof, upon the River <hi>Mulda;</hi> It conſiſts of four ſeveral Towns, each of which hath it's ſeveral Cuſtoms, Laws, and Magiſtrates: The principal is called the <hi>Old Town,</hi> adorned with goodly Buildings, a ſpacious Market-place, and a ſtately Counſel-houſe. The ſecond is called the <hi>New Town,</hi> ſeparated from the former by a deep and wide Ditch; The third is called the <hi>Little Town,</hi> divided from the <hi>Old</hi> by the River <hi>Mulda,</hi> joyned to it by a beautiful Bridge, conſiſting of twenty four Arches; and in this part is the Hill <hi>Rachine,</hi> on the ſides whereof are many fair and ſtately buildings belonging to the Nobility: and over them is a ſtrong Caſtle, and Pallace for the Kings place of reſidence: The fourth Town is that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> wherein they have five <hi>Synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues,</hi> and live after their own Law; The whole City is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther large than fair, the ſtreets in Winter dirty, and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38150:28"/> an ill ſmell in Summer; and it's but a weak place. In it is a Univerſity.</p>
                  <p>Neer to it was fought that Battel between the Duke of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia,</hi> and <hi>Bucquoy</hi> for the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, on the one ſide, with fifty thouſand men, and <hi>Frederick,</hi> newly Elected King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> and Count <hi>Thurne,</hi> with thirty thouſand men on the other ſide, wherein the Imperialiſts prevailed; the young Prince of <hi>Anhalt, Thurne, Saxon Weimar,</hi> and many others were taken Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Kings Ordinance ſurpriſed, and <hi>Prague</hi> forced to yield to the Conquerers, and the King and Queen of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> were driven preſently to fly into <hi>Sileſia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Moravia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Moravia</hi> deſcribed.</note>
                     <hi>Moravia</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Hungary;</hi> On the Weſt with <hi>Bohemia;</hi> On the North with <hi>Sileſia:</hi> and on the South with the <hi>Lower Auſtria,</hi> and the River <hi>Teja.</hi> It's the moſt fruitful place for Corn in all <hi>Germany,</hi> and hath much <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> which (as other doth) comes not out of Trees, but grows out of the Earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note>Places of moſt note in it, are, 1. <hi>Olmunts,</hi> on the River <hi>Mark,</hi> wherein is a ſmall Univerſity. 2. <hi>Brinn,</hi> on the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Schwats,</hi> the ſeat of the ancient Marqueſſes; and divers others about which there is nothing memorable. In this Country neer <hi>Sileſia,</hi> is the Spring-head of the River <hi>Odera.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sileſia</hi> deſcribed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sileſia</hi> deſcribed.</note>
                     <hi>Sileſia,</hi> called by the <hi>Dutch Schleſi,</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Poland;</hi> On the Weſt with <hi>Luſatia;</hi> On the North with <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and on the South with <hi>Moravia.</hi> It's wholly encompaſſed with Mountains except on the North, which lets in a ſharp air upon them; and the Midland is full of Woods.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The chief Towns.</note>The Chief Cities are; 1. <hi>Jagendorſe.</hi> 2. <hi>Munſterberg.</hi> 3. <hi>Glatz;</hi> the laſt Town that held out for King <hi>Frederick.</hi> 4. <hi>Glogaw,</hi> a ſtrong Town on the River <hi>Odera.</hi> 5. <hi>Nieſſe,</hi> on a River ſo named, a Biſhops See. 6. <hi>Breſlaw,</hi> in <hi>Latine, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ratiſlavia,</hi> a Biſhops See, on the River <hi>Odera:</hi> It's well
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38150:28"/> built, populous, and well contrived with open and even ſtreets. 7. <hi>Oppolen,</hi> upon the <hi>Odera,</hi> well fortified both by Art and Nature, having a ſtrong Caſtle in it, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="addenda">
                  <p rend="italic">The Arms of <hi rend="roman">Hungary</hi> are <hi rend="roman">Barre-wiſe</hi> of eight pieces, <hi rend="roman">Gules,</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Argent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A famous ſtory.</note> About the year 1600, <hi>Ferdinand de Gratz,</hi> who was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Emperor, was Governour of <hi>Steirmark, Carinthia,</hi> and <hi>Carniola;</hi> He married <hi>Mariana,</hi> the daughter of <hi>William,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> which Lady was ſuch a Jeſuited Papiſt, that ſhe would not enter into the limits of his Dominions until they were purged of Here ie, and Hereticks (as ſhe called them) and till the Liberties granted to thoſe of the <hi>Auguſtine Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> were taken away, which accordingly, the Arch-Duke (by the perſwaſion of the Jeſuits) did abrogate, and by Oath obliged himſelf to the Pope, that he would ſeverely proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all the Proteſtants which were within his Dominions;<note place="margin">Papiſh cruelty, and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity.</note> and accordingly he either baniſhed them, or Plundred, and Murthered them, which was proſecuted with ſuch cruelty and inhumanity by his Popiſh Agents, that they blew up their very Churches with Gun-powder, and raged againſt the very bones of the Dead, not ſuffering them to lie quietly in their graves (which are common and allowed to all men) inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as what the <hi>Turks</hi> had ſpared, was not ſpared by them. At the demoliſhing of their Churches in <hi>Gratz,</hi> they digged up the Body of <hi>William Zimmerman,</hi> an eminent Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Miniſter of that place, and threw it into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Mur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againſt theſe outrages the Proteſtants pleaded the Treaty at <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> and challenged the Oath and Faith plighted to them by this Arch-Duke himſelf, by which (in the year 1581) he confirmed his Fathers agreement with the States, during which ſpace of above eighteen years, he had received from them the Summe of nine hundred thouſand <hi>Florens</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> is the price of their Liberty of Conſcience; yet nothing would prevail to ſtop his violent proceedings againſt them.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Ferdinands</hi> ſucceſs was anſwerable to this Injuſtice;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38150:29"/> For about this time he was engaged in the ſiege of <hi>Canyſia,</hi> held by the <hi>Turks,</hi> wherein he was aſſiſted by <hi>Aldobrand,</hi> the Popes Legate, with his <hi>Italian</hi> Forces; and by the advice of <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> Count of <hi>Thurne,</hi> there were none ſuffered to be liſted in their Army but <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, leſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of any Proteſtants ſhould cauſe the enterpriſe to miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Governour of <hi>Canyſia</hi> at this time, was <hi>Haſanes,</hi> who with eight hundred men, and as many more from <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth,</hi> and <hi>Buda,</hi> that through the negligence of <hi>Orphus Gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius, Ferdinands</hi> General of the Ordinance, gat into the City, he defended it reſolutely. This <hi>Orphus</hi> whilſt he was buſie in filling the ditches with wood from the adjoyning For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, was ſhot with a Culverin bullet, and killed. The <hi>Turks</hi> made frequent, and vigorous Sallies wherein they killed many; and though the Emperor <hi>Matthias</hi> ſent ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men to aſſiſt and animate his Couſin, yet was the Siege ſpun out till Winter came, which with Froſts and Storms, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced them to leave their Station (a thouſand Horſemen being frozen to Death in one night:) They were alſo worn out with Snow, Hunger, Wearineſs, and Watching in attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Active and Inductrious Enemy, ſo that they were faign with diſhonour to raiſe their Siege, and that in ſuch haſt that they left all their Ordinance for a prey to the <hi>Turks,</hi> who preſently after their departure, ſlew all their ſick, and wounded Souldiers that they left in their Camp; and thus it pleaſed God to preſerve the Proteſtants, whom they would not admit into their Army, and the blow fell upon them, who were the Perſecutors of them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>NEWLY EXTANT KNOWLEDGE &amp; PRACTICE, Or, a Plain diſcourſe of the chief things neceſſary to be KNOWN, BELIEVED, &amp; PRACTISED, in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to SALVATION; <hi>Very uſeful for Private Families;</hi> By <hi>Samuel Cradock;</hi> Sould by <hi>William Miller,</hi> at the Gilded Acorn in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38150:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
